<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The crie of England A sermon preached at Paules Crosse in September 1593 by Adam Hill Doctor of Diuinitie, &amp; published at the request of the then Lord Maior of the citie of London, and others the aldermen his brethren</title>
            <author>Hill, Adam, d. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115191</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850410</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850410</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15611</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15611)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1275:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The crie of England A sermon preached at Paules Crosse in September 1593 by Adam Hill Doctor of Diuinitie, &amp; published at the request of the then Lord Maior of the citie of London, and others the aldermen his brethren</title>
                  <author>Hill, Adam, d. 1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 111, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ed. Allde, for B. Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The date in title possibly a mistake, should be 1592?--STC.</note>
                  <note>On Genesis xviii 21-2.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CRIE OF ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at Paules Croſse in Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1593. by <hi>Adam Hill</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Diuinitie, &amp; <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at the requeſt of the then Lord Maior of</hi> the Citie of London, and others the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Ed. Allde, for B. Norton. 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE THE Lord Maior of the famous Citie of London, and the right Worſhipfull the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen his Bretheren, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the ſame, Adam Hill Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsor of Diuinitie, wiſheth grace, peace, and life euerlaſting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be foure things in the earth verie ſmal, &amp; verie wiſe (as witneſſeth wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi>):<note place="margin">Prou. 30.25, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the Piſmires, a people not ſtrong, yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare they their meate in the ſummer; the Cunnies a people not mightie, yet make they their houſes in the rocke; the Graſhopper hath no King, yet go they foorth all by bands; the Spider taketh hold with his handes, and yet is he in Kings Pallaces:</hi> So muſt we prouide now in the ſummer
<pb facs="tcp:15611:3"/> time, while the Goſpell ſhineth out of the face of Chriſt Ieſus, againſt the winter, which hath in it three moneths, death, iudgement, and hell: that as the Emmet eſcapeth the annoyance of the three winter moneths, ſo wee may eſcape the terrour of death, the rigor of Gods iudgement, and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell. The Cunnies build their houſe in the rocke: ſo we may not truſt to our riches which are vncertaine, to our bowe which will breake, to our ſpeare which ſhall bee knapt aſunder, to our horſe which is a vaine thing, to our hoaſts of men which are but fleſh, to our Captaines which are but locuſts, to men which are mortall, or to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ſhall die; but to the Lord, which can keepe our eyes from teares, our feete from falling, and our life from death. The Graſhoppers albeit they haue no king, yet they goe foorth by armies: we haue a father to rule in the houſe, a preacher to teach in the Church, a gracious Prince, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie honorable Senators to rule our Realme, &amp; yet there is ſtrife in euerie houſe, ſedition in euerie Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſects in euerie Church; and therefore our houſe will fall, our kingdome ſhall be deſolate, and our church will be the ſinagogue of ſatan. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is in Kings pallaces: but wee dwell ſome of vs in the luſts of the fleſh, ſome in the treaſures of the world, and ſome are as enuious as the diuell; fewe there are that ſay with Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb facs="tcp:15611:3"/> yea and fainteth for the Courtes of the Lord, for my hart and my fleſh reioice in the liuing God.</hi> To moue my countrimen therefore to a generall, ſpeedie, and heartie repentaunce, I haue laid downe in this treatiſe, the crie not of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but of England; which if it be diligentlie weighed,<note place="margin">Luke. 21.34.</note> I doubt not but we ſhall <hi>take heede to our ſelues, leaſt our hearts be oppreſſed with ſurfetting and drunkennes, and cares of this life.</hi> We ſhall be <hi>watchfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 24.24. Mich. 6.8. Rom: 12.12. Rom. 12.11.</note> we ſhall <hi>doo iuſtlye and loue mercie,</hi> we ſhall be <hi>inſtant in praier,</hi> we ſhall be <hi>feruent in the ſpirit,</hi> we ſhall not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere in ſinne but continue in praier without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſaying: <hi>Turne thy face away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.9.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, &amp; blot out al our offences:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 19.8, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not againſt vs the former iniquities but make haſt &amp; let thy tender mercy preuent vs: help vs O God of our ſaluation for the glorie of thy name, and deliuer vs, and be mercifull to our ſinnes for thy names ſake: ſo we thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſheepe of thy paſture ſhal praiſe thee for euer, and from generation to generation will ſet forth thy praiſe:</hi> which God giue vs grace to doo for his ſonnes ſake Chriſt Jeſus: to whom with the holie Ghoſt be all honor and glorie for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord,</hi> Adam Hill, <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15611:4"/>
            <head>THE CRIE OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Geneſ. 18. ver. 21, 22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Becauſe the crie of Sodome &amp; Gomorrha is great, and becauſe their ſinne is exceeding greeuous, I will goe downe now, and ſee whether they haue done altogether according to that crie which is come vnto me, and if not, that I may know.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F all the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, there is not one example more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently vſed of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles to feare the people from ſinne, than thys generall, ſeuere, and fearful deſtruction of the <hi>Sodomites.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ier. 49.40.</note> 
               <hi>As God deſtroyed Sodome and Gomorrha with the places thereabout ſaith the Lord, ſo ſhall no man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15611:5"/> dwell there, neither ſhall the ſonne of man remain there.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 4.11.</note> So ſaith the Prophet <hi>Amos, I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen them as God ouerthrew Sodome and Gomorrha, and ye were as a firebrand pluckt out of the fire, yet haue yee not repented.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Zephanie</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Zeph. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Surely Moab ſhall bee as Sodome, and Ammon as Gomorrha, the breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nettles and ſalt pits, and a perpetuall deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> So likewiſe it is ſaid in the Euangeliſts, <hi>And whoſoeuer ſhall not receiue you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.14. Mat. 6.11. Luke. 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>nor heare your words, when ye depart out of that houſe, or that citie, ſhake off the duſt of your feete, truly J ſay vnto you, it ſhall be eaſier for them of the land of Sodom and Gomorrha in the day of iudgement than for that citie.</hi> And in the ſecond Epiſtle of S. <hi>Peter</hi> it is ſaid,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>And turned the cities of Sodom &amp; Gomorrha into aſhes, condemned them &amp; made them an enſample vnto them that ſhould afterward liue vngodly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 7.</note> So in <hi>Iude, As Sodom and Gomorrha, and the cities round about them which in like manner as they did, committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and followed ſtrange fleſh, are ſet downe for an enſample, and ſuffer the vengeance of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As all the Prophets and Apoſtles, yea and Chriſt himſelfe haue vnto their hearers, ſet downe Sodome and Gomorrha as an enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods iuſtice againſt ſin &amp; impenitent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15611:5"/> ſinners: ſo doo I purpoſe (by Gods grace) to handle this fearfull panolethrie or vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to this Citie of London; aſſuring my ſelfe, that if this exhortation worke not in you a broken heart, you ſhall by the yron rod of Gods wrath, be broken in peeces like a potters veſſell, you ſhall be like the breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nettles and ſalt pits, you ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue a perpetual deſolation in earth which is lamentable, but alſo ſuffer the vengeance of eternall fire which is intollerable.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ene Sodom and London.</note> Sodom was in a frutefull valley, ſo is London: in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there were gorgeous houſes and fayre workes, ſo there are in London: in Sodome they did eate and drinke, and fulfill the luſts of the fleſh, ſo doo they in London: Sodom was in captiuitie vnder <hi>Chedor Laomer,</hi> and freed by <hi>Abraham;</hi> London (&amp; all England) was in ſubiection to the Pope, &amp; hath been freed by our gracious Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had <hi>Lot</hi> (the Preacher of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) ſent vnto them whoſe ſpirit they vexed; London hath had manie godly Fathers ſent vnto them, whom they reuile: Sodome was not moued to repentance, neither with their captiuitie nor deliuerance, therfore they wer deſtroied; Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not moued neither with perſecution nor peace to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, therfore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15611:6"/> London, except it ſpeedily repent, ſhall bee brought to a perpetual deſolation, and to the vengeance of eternall fire.</p>
            <p>In the ſinnes of Sodome are three things to be noted: firſt, the euidencie of their ſins, which is noted in the word <hi>crie:</hi> ſecondly, they had manie ſinnes, which is noted in the word <hi>great:</hi> thirdly, their ſins were haynous, which is noted in theſe words, <hi>exceeding gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous.</hi> The euidencie of ſin as it was in Sodom ſo was it ſaith <hi>Eſay</hi> in Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">Eſa. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>The triall of their countenance teſtifieth againſt them, yea, they declare their ſinnes as Sodome, they hide them not.</hi> And are not the ſinnes of England manifeſt? doo our Papiſts hide their ſinne? doo they not call idolatrie catholike religion?<note place="margin">Manifeſt ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</note> they are worſhippers of images, which are vaine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable &amp; abhominable. Images are vaine both in reſpect of the maker, which is the cauſe efficient, &amp; in reſpect of the matter, in reſpect alſo of the forme, and of the end.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the maker images are vaine, for he is vaine in thought, in word, in deed, and in his eſſence:<note place="margin">Pſa. 94: 11.</note> in thought, for <hi>the Lord knoweth the thoughts of men, they are but vaine.</hi> In word,<note place="margin">Pſa. 12.2.</note> for <hi>they talke of vanitie euerie one to his neighbour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 101.5.</note> In deed, <hi>for they are vanitie, and the worke of errors, in the time of their viſitation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15611:6"/> they ſhall periſh.</hi> In eſſence,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.11.</note> for <hi>ſurely euerie man is vanitie:</hi> man therefore beeing vaine in thought, word, deed, &amp; eſſence, muſt needs make a vaine image. The matter alſo of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is vaine, for they are made either of gold, ſiluer, braſſe, clay, ſtone, or wood: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet <hi>Baruch</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Bar. 6.5, 6, 11</note> 
               <hi>Theſe Gods of wood, ſiluer and of gold, can neither defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from theeues and robbers: for they that are ſtrongeſt take away their gold, ſiluer, and apparell wherewith they be cloathed, and when they haue it, they get them away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The forme alſo of images is vaine, for <hi>they haue eyes and ſee not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>noſes haue they and ſmell not, eares and heare not, mouthes and ſpeake not, feete and walke not.</hi> Finally, images are vaine alſo in reſpect of the end, for they help ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the teacher, nor the hearer, nor the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, nor the receiuer of the ſacrament, nor him that praieth. Therfore the Sun, Moone, and Starres, are better than images, nay, the dore of the houſe, or a ſcar-crow in the fields is better, for all theſe doo ſerue vnto ſome end, but images to no end.</p>
            <p>The images therefore of the Papiſts are as vaine as the images of the heathen, and ſo are they al as vnprofitable: For as Paul ſaith, they are nothing. <hi>An idoll is nothing in the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.4.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15611:7"/> For this cauſe <hi>Zachary</hi> calleth the vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miniſter,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>an idoll paſtor:</hi> ſo the Magiſtrate that doth not <hi>defend the poore and fatherles, &amp; ſee that ſuch as be in neceſsitie &amp; need,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
               <hi>haue right,</hi> is an idoll magiſtrate: the father that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not vp his children in the feare of the Lord, is an idoll father: ſo the husband that loueth not his wife as his owne fleſh, as his owne bodie, &amp; as Chriſt loued the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is an idoll husband: the wife that is fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the child that is diſobedient, the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that is vnfaithfull, the ſubiect that is diſloyal, are al idolls, inſufficient for anie ſpirituall vſe and therefore vnles they repent, they ſhal be burſt in peeces by the yron ſcepter of Gods iuſtice, and ſo deſtroyed, as they ſhall neuer be builded againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The idolatrie of the Papiſts as abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as the idolatrie of the heathen.</note>As the idolatrie of the Papiſts is vaine &amp; vnprofitable: ſo is it as abhominable as the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie of the heathen; for as the heathen in the time of warre did inuocate <hi>Mars</hi> &amp; <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lona,</hi> ſo the Papiſts doo inuocate S. <hi>George:</hi> the heathen in pouertie went to <hi>Ceres,</hi> the Papiſts to Saint <hi>Anne:</hi> the heathen in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes went to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> the Papiſts to Saint <hi>Roche:</hi> the heathen in captiuitie went to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the Papiſts to Saint <hi>Leonard:</hi> the heathen in hunger went to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the Papiſts to S.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15611:7"/> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbane:</hi> the heathen in ſea-ſtormes went to <hi>Neptune,</hi> the papiſts to Saint <hi>Nicholas:</hi> the heathen in child-birth went to <hi>Juno,</hi> the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts they went to our Ladie. And heerein they doo offend moſt greeuouſly for three cauſes: firſt becauſe they attribute to the Saints omnipotencie: ſecondly, becauſe they attribute to them vniuerſall knowledge: and thirdly, becauſe they make them more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull than Chriſt. Further, as the heathen did conſecrate Troy to <hi>Neptune,</hi> Cyprus to <hi>Venus,</hi> Athens to <hi>Minerua,</hi> Carthage to <hi>Juno,</hi> and Rome to <hi>Jupiter:</hi> ſo the papiſts dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Spaine to Saint <hi>James,</hi> Germanie to Saint <hi>George,</hi> France to Saint <hi>Denis,</hi> Scotland to ſaint <hi>Andrew,</hi> Ireland to ſaint <hi>Patricke,</hi> and Rome to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> And as the heathen haue conſecrated their head to <hi>Minerua,</hi> their heart to <hi>Juno,</hi> their breaſt to <hi>Mars,</hi> their tongue to <hi>Mercurie,</hi> their armes to <hi>Hercules,</hi> their liuer to <hi>Cupid,</hi> their throate to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> their bellie to <hi>Ceres,</hi> their ſecretes to <hi>Venus,</hi> their palmes to <hi>Apollo,</hi> and theyr ſpirite to <hi>Jupiter:</hi> ſo the papiſts haue for the head-ache <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> for their eyes <hi>Otilia,</hi> for the teeth <hi>Apollonia,</hi> for the necke S. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> and for the bellie <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> And as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then dedicated the boare to <hi>Mars,</hi> the goate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15611:8"/> to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the peacocke to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the ſwan to <hi>Apollo,</hi> the doue to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> the night-crow to <hi>Minerua,</hi> the wheate to <hi>Ceres,</hi> honie to <hi>Mercurie,</hi> and the roſe to <hi>Cupid:</hi> ſo the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts conſecrated their ſheepe to <hi>Vandolius,</hi> their horſe to <hi>Eulogius,</hi> their oxen to <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and their pigs to Saint <hi>Anthonie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore it is an abhomination to call vpon anie but on him, on whom we beleeue: ſo to commit our ſelues, or ours, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or cuſtodie of the creatures, which <hi>ſhould dwell vnder the protection of the higheſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.1. Pſal. 18.2.</note> and which <hi>ſhould haue the Lord to be our rocke, and our fortreſſe, and him that deliuereth vs, our God, and our ſtrength, in him we ſhould truſt, our ſhield, the horne alſo of our ſaluation, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge,</hi> is a great abhomination: for <hi>the honoring of abhominable images,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sap. 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>is the beginning, the cauſe, and the end of al euil.</hi> I end therefore with this notable ſaying of S. <hi>Ierome</hi> writing vpon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierome in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech.</note> 
               <q>Curſed is euerie man that putteth his truſt in man, though they bee Saints, or though they be Prophets.</q> Becauſe therefore idolaters are the cauſe of the ouerthrowe of the land: God in his holy word commandeth that they ſhould be deſtroyed.<note place="margin">Deu. 13.6. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>If thy brother the ſonne of thy mother, or thy owne ſonne or thy daughter, or the wife that lieth in thy boſome, or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15611:8"/> thy friend which is as thine owne ſoule, entice thee ſecretly, ſaying: Let vs goe and ſerue other Gods (which thou haſt not knowen, thou J ſay, nor thy fathers) anie of the gods of the people which are round about you, nere vnto thee or far from thee, from the one ende of the earth vnto the other: thou ſhalt not conſent vnto him, nor heare him, neither ſhall thy eye pitie him, nor ſhewe mercie, nor keepe him ſecret, but ſhalt euen kill him, thy hand ſhall be firſt vppon him to put him to death, and then the hand of all the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſinne not onely of idolatrie is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, but alſo the ſinne of blaſphemie.<note place="margin">Manifeſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemie in England.</note> What bargaine almoſt is made without ſwearing? what oath is miniſtred in the iudgement ſeat without forſwearing? what ſports without blaſphemie? what countrie, what citie, what towne, what houſe, or what tongue is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this ſinne of ſwearing? the olde man ſweareth by cuſtome, the yong man &amp; childe by imitation, the gentleman ſweareth of luſtines, the poore ſweareth for neceſsity, the thief ſweareth to couer his fault, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to denie her crime: and albeit not man but the Lord our God commaundeth vs ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not holde him guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in vaine:</hi> yet all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15611:9"/> the deſperate people of this declining age, are ſo giuen to ſwearing, as though no man could be ſaued happily, vnleſſe he did ſweare continually. Can a bitter fountaine ſend out ſweete water? no more can a blaſphemous mouth ſpeake to the praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring drawen from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God. Pſal. 139.3.</note>There be fiue things in God which euerie blaſphemer ſhould conſider of: the firſt is, that he is preſent in all places, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; <hi>Thou compaſſeſt my pathes, and my lying downe, and art accuſtomed to all my wayes.</hi> Secondly, he knoweth all things, for <hi>there is not a word</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) in my mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.4.</note> 
               <hi>but thou knoweſt it all, O Lord.</hi> Thirdly, there is truth in the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>God loueth no wickednes, neither ſhall anie euill dwell with him, the fooliſh ſhal not ſtand in his ſight, for he hateth them that worke iniquitie, he will deſtroy them that ſpeake lies.</hi> Fourthly, God is righteous, and therfore the Pſalmiſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.137.</note> 
               <hi>Righteous art thou (O Lord) and righteous are thy iudgements, thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded iuſtice by thy teſtimonies, and truth eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is righteous: firſt, becauſe he iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in equitie, <hi>With righteouſnes ſhall he iudge the world, and the people with equitie:</hi> ſecondly, becauſe he iudgeth without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.9. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be vppon the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15611:9"/> ſoule of euerie man that doth euill, of the Iew firſt and alſo of the Grecian, but to euerie man that doth good ſhall be honor and glorie, and peace, to the Jew firſt, and alſo to the Grecian: for there is no reſpect of perſons with God.</hi> Thirdly, God is iuſt, becauſe he leaueth no ſinne vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; <hi>Binde not two ſinnes together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Syr. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>for there ſhall not one be vnpuniſhed.</hi> For as no vertue is of God vnrewarded, ſo there ſhall be no ſin vnpuniſhed. Fourthly and laſtly, in God is all power; <hi>Our God is in heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.3.</note> 
               <hi>he doth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer pleaſeth him.</hi> From heauen he caſt down the Angels, from Paradice <hi>Adam,</hi> hee made the earth to ſwallow vp <hi>Corah,</hi> the flouds to couer <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoaſt, the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> to be ſlaine in the temple, <hi>Jezabel</hi> to be caſt out of her chamber window, <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes</hi> to be murdred in his bed, and <hi>Ely</hi> to breake his necke ſitting on the threſholde. Wherefore excellent is that ſaying of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard in Pſal. 139.</note> God is in himſelfe as <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt: <q>in the world, as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and gouernor of it; in the angels, as the fauor and beautie of them: in the church, as a father of a family in his houſe; in the ſoule, as a bridegroome in his chamber: in the iuſt, as a helper and protector; in the reprobate, as a dread and horror. Whither ſhall I goe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15611:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15611:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15611:11"/> from thy ſpirit? no man goeth from him, but to him: from his ſeueritie, to his goodnes; from an angrie God, to an appeaſed: For what place can receiue him that flieth, but there thou maiſt finde his preſence?</q> God is preſent, therefore the blaſphemer ſhould feare him; God knoweth all things, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the blaſphemer ſhould praiſe him: in God is truth, therefore the blaſphemer ſhould hate lies: in God is iuſtice, therefore he rewardeth the good and puniſheth the euill: in God is power, therefore he can doo what pleaſeth him: fire, haile, ſtormes and tempeſts fulfill his commaundements: yea, there are ſpirites created for vengeance, and in their ſuriouſneſſe they haſten their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they wil not ouerpaſſe the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord. The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ier. 4.2. The 2. argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ſwearing, drawen from the manner and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er thereof.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord liueth, in truth, iudgement, &amp; righteouſnes:</hi> in <hi>truth,</hi> in reſpect of the thing; in <hi>iudgement,</hi> in reſpect of the ſwearer; in <hi>iuſtice,</hi> in reſpect of the cauſe: truth excludeth a falſe oath, iudgement a raſh oath, iuſtice an vnlawfull oath but our blaſphemers ſweare not in truth, but in fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood; not in iudgement, but raſhly; not in iuſtice (that is firſt for the glorie of God, ſecondly, for the ſafetie of their neighbour,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15611:11"/> thirdly, for their own neceſsitie, and fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they are required of the Magiſtrate for iuſt cauſes) but in common ſpeach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully, in buying and ſelling deceiptfully, and in ſporting and playing moſt damnably. Further,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.25. Pſal. 32.5. Eſa. 50.4. 1. Theſ. 5.14. Pſal. 51.14. The 5. argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ſwearing, drawen from the vſe of the tongue.</note> the tongue being giuen of God <hi>to ſpeake the truth, to confeſſe our ſinnes, to teach, to comfort the afflicted,</hi> &amp; laſtly, <hi>to praiſe the Lord:</hi> the blaſphemer ſetteth forth leaſing, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his ſinnes, is an enſample of corrupt manners, bringeth no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort but the plague of God to his houſe, and diſhonoureth the Lord, whom hee ſhould praiſe with ſoule, heart, heart, tongue, fleſh, and with all hys powers &amp; members for euer. A thiefe ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth but for neceſsitie, but a blaſphemer ſweareth in a brauerie: the harlots do ſinne but in darknes, the blaſphemer offendeth openly: the couetous man offendeth but ſeldome, the blaſphemer often, &amp; at euerie word: the ſlaunderer offendeth but againſt his brother, but the blaſphemer diſhonoreth God his father. There are but 3. ſorts of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages in the world,<note place="margin">The 4. argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt ſwearing, drawen from the cuſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſpeech. Pſal. 84.4.</note> the beſt is the heauenly language, whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> thus writeth, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that dwel in thy houſe, O Lord, they ſhall alwaies be praiſing &amp; magnifying thy name.</hi> There is another language that is earthly,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15611:12"/> whereof Saint <hi>John</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.31.</note> 
               <hi>He that is of the earth, is of the earth, and ſpeaketh of the earth.</hi> There is alſo an infernall language, which is nothing but <hi>curſing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 8.21.</note> therefore as it was ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 14.40.</note> 
               <hi>Surely thou art one of them, for thou art of Galilea, and thy ſpeach is like;</hi> ſo becauſe of the abundaunce of the heart the tongue ſpeaketh: you may thereby know who is of heauen, who of earth, &amp; who of hell. They that praiſe the Lord are heauenly indeed, &amp; their conuerſation is in heauen: they that ſpeake of the earth, are earthly; but they that curſe and ſweare, are alreadie damned, their ſpeach is like. As he is a Spaniard that naturally and properly ſpeaketh Spaniſh, &amp; he a French-man that ſpeaketh French, and hea Welch-man that ſpeaketh Welch: ſo he that ſpeaketh of the praiſes of God is a ſaint, hee that ſpeaketh of the earth is an earthly man, and he that is a ſwearer, is of the diuel. The bitter ſtream proueth the fountaine to bee bitter, the leaues ſhew what the tree is: ſo the blaſphemous words of wicked men doo ſhew that they come from the bitter roote of infidelitie. No man receiueth gold but hee weigheth it: no man hath ground but he encloſeth it: why then? do not our ſwearers weigh their words, and hedge in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15611:12"/> their tongue, becauſe as S. <hi>James</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>It is ſet on fire of hell:</hi> when therefore hell fire cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, the blaſphemers of Gods name will ceaſe. And hereunto agreeth the ſaying of Ieſus the ſonne of Syrach,<note place="margin">Syr. 23.13.15.</note> 
               <hi>Vſe not thy mouth to ignorant raſhnes, for therein is the occaſion of ſinne: the man that is accuſtomed to opprobrious words, will neuer be reformed all the dayes of his life;</hi> and ſuch a one was <hi>Shimei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. sam. 16.7.</note> King <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth hauing an accuſtomed ſwearer in his Court, cut off his lips: and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of his Courtiers, why he executed ſo greeuous a puniſhment? hee aunſwered, Would my lips were ſo cut off, that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a ſwearer in my Kingdome. But the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe why ſwearing is ſo frequent in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is the negligence of Princes,<note place="margin">Why ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh not this offence; and the fearfulneſſe of the Miniſters, who dare not reproue this ſin in Gentlemen and noble perſonages, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the euill example of parents: who neither leaue this ſinne themſelues, nor yet puniſh it ſeuerely in their poſterite. The blaſphemies and periuries of England, haue infected euerie Countrie, Citie and Houſe of this land: therefore without a generall, heartie, and ſpeedie repentance, perpetuall deſolation, &amp; the vengeance of eternall fire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15611:13"/> will fall vpon the father and the ſonne, the paſtor and the people, the priuate man and the magiſtrate for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt ſinne in England.</note>Prophanation of the Sabaoth is another of the euident ſinnes of England. We are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to hallow our Sabaoth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Exo.</hi> 20 11. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. and yet in all places, and of the greater part of the people of this land, the ſabaoth is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned with dauncing, ſtage-playing, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayting, bowling, &amp; with all manner of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations. And not onely the holy word of God, but the ancient Fathers and the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Law doo ſpeake of the ſanctification of the ſabaoth.<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> on the 32. pſal. ſaith, It is better to digge than to daunce on the ſabaoth.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. in homil. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> in his 48. homily ſaith, <q>Where wanton dauncing is, there no doubt the diuell is preſent: for God hath giuen vs theſe members not to daunce, but that we ſhould walke modeſtly, and not to daunce impudently after the manner of Camels (for not only women but Camels daunce vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently) but that we ſhould ſtand in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of the Angells: and if the bodie bee deformed by dauncing, how much more is the ſoule? in theſe daunces the diuell daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15611:13"/> with theſe daunces they are deceiued of the miniſters of the diuell.<note place="margin">Ambroſe Lib. 3. de virg.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his 3. booke of Virgins, thus writeth: What ſay ye, O holy women? you ſee what ye ought to teach &amp; vnteach your daughters: ſhe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, but the daughter of an harlot; for ſhe that is chaſt &amp; ſhamefaſt, teacheth her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren religion, &amp; not dancing. And as theſe inueigh againſt dauncing,<note place="margin">Lactant. lib. 4. cap. 20.</note> ſo doth <hi>Lactantius</hi> againſt ſtage-playing, in his 6. book, cha. 20. I know not (ſaith he) wherein there can be a more vicious corruption than in plaies: for the Enterludes doo ſpeak of the deflouring of virgins, &amp; of the loues of harlots: &amp; the more eloquent they are that haue fained thoſe abhominations, the more the elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the ſentences doth perſwade, and they ſticke more eaſily in the memory of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, the verſes which are numerous and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent. The tragicall hiſtories alſo doo ſet before our eies, the patricides and inceſts of euill kings, &amp; doo ſhew their wickednes on the ſtage: the vnchaſt geſtures of the plaiers alſo what doo they teach, or ſtirre vp in vs but luſts? whoſe bodies being made weake and wanton in imitating the going and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell of women, doo counterſaite vnchaſt women with vnhoneſt geſtures.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15611:14"/>
            <p>
               <q>What ſhall I ſpeake of ballads, which teach the doctrine of corruptions, which teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulteries whiles they feigne, and by feigned adulteries inſtruct to true? what may yong men and maides doo, when they ſee theſe things to be done, and to be ſeene of al men gladly and without ſhame? they are warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therefore what they maye doo, and they are inflamed with luſt, which is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked with ſeeing, and euerie one accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his ſexe prefigureth himſelfe in thoſe images, and doo allowe them, while they laugh at them; and vices cleauing vnto them they returne to their houſes moſt corrupt: neither onely children, which ſhould not be endued with vices in their firſt age, but alſo olde men, whom it becommeth not to ſin, doo fall into the ſame path of iniquities. It is cleare by this that hath been alleadged, that as the Prophets and Apoſtles haue taught the ſanctification of the Sabaoth: ſo the Fathers haue walked in the ſame ſteps; yea, godly Princes haue made lawes for ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying the Sabaoth. <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Anthemius</hi> (being religious Princes) writing to <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> commanded him in theſe words; That the feſtiuall dayes being dedicated to the excellent Maieſtie of God, ſhould neither
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15611:14"/> be occupied in paſtime and pleaſure, neither be prophaned in exacting of tributes: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee decree (ſay they) that the Sunday ſhall be reuerently honoured, that it ſhal be exempted from all buſines; in this day let no ſuretiſhip be taken, let no man be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appeare: let no man vſe pleading, and let no cauſes or matters of controuerſies be heard. And a little after it followeth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we ſuffer, that this day being exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from all trauell, ſhould be ſpent in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes and filthy delights, that there be any enterlude or pageant plaid on the dominical day, or anie game or paſtime in the place of exerciſe called <hi>Circus,</hi> or the lamentable ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctale of beaſts: yea although the ſolemnity of our birth happen vpon this day, let it be deferred: if anie man on this day ſhall haue anie acceſſe to ſpectacles, or vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of priuate or publike affaires, ſhall be an Apparitor or Sergeant to anie Iudge, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olating or breaking theſe Statutes, let him looſe the commoditie of warfare, and runne into the preſcription of attainder.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The holie Prophetes and Apoſtles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto vs the hallowing of the Sabaoth, the Fathers exhort vs to the ſame, the lawes of godly Princes commaund it, yet we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15611:15"/> in England wilfull contemners of this precept. The ſanctification of the Sabaoth conſiſteth in foure things.<note place="margin">The ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Sabaoth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in 4. things.</note> Firſt of all, holy men ought to enter into the Church, where the Goſpell muſt be expounded and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; by the which the Auditorie may learn what to thinke of God, what is the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, and how the name of GOD may be glorified. Secondly, there muſt be praiers &amp; petitions made vnto God for the neceſsitie of all men. Thirdly, we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the goodnes of God, giuing thankes for his daily and ineſtimable benefites; which giuing of thankes excludeth foure things, firſt contempt of God, ſecondly forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, thirdly malice, fourthly the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of Gods creatures. And the ſacraments muſt religiouſly be celebrated, if the time, occaſion, and cuſtome of the Church doo ſo require: for it is chiefly required in the fourth precept, that we ſhould diligently obſerue and deuoutly exerciſe the holy ſacraments and holy rytes of the Church being lawfull, profitable, and neceſſarie. Fourthly, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and beneficencie muſt take place in the Church, all men muſt learne daily to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall in giuing of almes priuately, but to be moſt liberall publiquely whenſoeuer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15611:15"/> of the time and opportunitie ſhal ſo require. Whereas we ſhould ſpend our ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both in hearing and reading of the word of God, we ſpend it in reading of vaine &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked pamphlets: wheras we ſhuld then make petition to God for our neceſsities, we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vp &amp; downe after deceiptfull vanities: wher we ſhuld be thankful to god, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on that day for his benefits, we miſſpend our time in idle paſtimes: &amp; laſtly, wher we ſhuld be liberal to the poor, we are prodigal to minſtrels, bearkeepers plaiers, &amp; to al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of vanities: for aſmuch then as al diuines &amp; godly princes haue approued the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this day, &amp; now all ſorts of people prophane the ſame, the old aſwel as the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, the father aſwel as the ſon, the maſter aſwell as the ſeruant, the miniſter aſwel as the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, &amp; the magiſtrate with the priuate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; neither the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of God is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor the example of our maker imitated, nor the admonitions of the prophets regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor the counſels of the apoſtles follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor the reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions of the fathers eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be but this prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Sabaoth ſo generall, ſo frequent, &amp; ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall, crieth to the Lord for a perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, &amp; for the vengeance of eternal fire.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15611:16"/>
            <p>Murther alſo is another ſinne that crieth for vengeance,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>The voice of thy brothers blood</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>crieth vnto me from the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Murther a manifeſt ſin that crieth for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</note> To looſe our wealth it is greeuous, but to looſe our good name more greeuous, but to looſe our life that is moſt greeuous of all. Firſt it is an heinous offence that one man ſhould kill another: ſecondly it is more hainous, when a ſuperior killeth an inferior: thirdly, it is a moſt hainous offence, when one bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther killeth another, as <hi>Cain</hi> killed <hi>Abel:</hi> fourthly it is more deteſtable, when a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man killeth a righteous: fifthly, &amp; that for the ſincere worſhip of God: ſixtly, if he doo it of a pretended hatred: and ſeuenthly if he doo it after admonition. In England man killeth man, the lord the tennant, the brother his brother, the wicked the good, &amp; that for the true worſhip of God, and of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and after godly admonition. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> cried from the earth vnto the Lord, ſo doth the blood of the Saints ſhed in the late daies of Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> crie for vengeance againſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note>
               <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man let his blood be ſhed: for after his owne image God made man.</hi> Firſt heere wee learne that man was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15611:16"/> made to praiſe God: whoſoeuer then killeth man, hindreth the glorie of God. Secondly, how was man created? in righteouſnes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, mercie, truth: theſe vertues being eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall in God, are accidentall in vs: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore murthereth a man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth thoſe vertues, wherein man dooth participate with the nature of God. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſith God made man after his owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: here we learne that God loueth man aboue all the creatures of the world, &amp; we ought not to hate him whom God loueth. Fourthly, ſith man is the image of God and doth excell all creatures; whoſoeuer mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth him, deſtroyeth the moſt excellent workmanſhip of God.</p>
            <p>But how little we regard theſe things, it is manifeſt by the wilfull murthers often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in and about London; whoſe blood no doubt crieth to God, as <hi>Abels</hi> did, out of the earth. For firſt God is the Iudge of the quicke and the dead. Secondly, he is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenger of all euill; for albeit men will wink at murther, yet God will not. And therfore the Prophet Dauid crieth out;<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>O God to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vengeance belongeth, thou God to whom venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance belongeth, ſhew thy ſelfe: ariſe thou Judge of the world, and reward the proud after their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15611:17"/> deſeruing.</hi> Thirdly, the iuſt (as <hi>Abel</hi> was) do peculiarly belong to God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>The poore commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe to thee: for thou art the helper of the fatherleſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>He that toucheth you (ſaith the Lord) toucheth the apple of mine eye.</hi> Precious therefore is the blood of the Saints in Gods ſight, and ſhall be of God himſelfe in time auenged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sodometrie &amp; who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dome crie for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</note>Sodometrie alſo and vnnatural luſt crieth to God for vengeance &amp; puniſhment. King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth of famous memorie, when he viſited the Abbies of England by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Lee, Richard Layton,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bedel</hi> Archdeacon of Cornwall, being Doctors of the Law, &amp; by <hi>Thomas Barthlet</hi> publique Notarie, in the yere of our Lord God 1538. In the Abbey of Battell were found 16 So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, in Chriſt-church at Canterbutie 9. and in euery Abbey were found ſome to be Sodomites, others to be adultrers, ſome ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing foure, ſome fiue, ſome ten, ſome twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie harlots, as in a Book called a Breuiarie of thoſe things that were found in Abbeyes, Conuents, &amp;c. it doth at large appeare. And becauſe that Sodometrie and whoredome had made them verie infamous, one of their owne friends thus wrote of them,
<q>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15611:17"/>
                  <l>Non male ſunt monachis grata indita nomina patrum</l>
                  <l>Cum numere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t natos hic &amp; vbique ſuos.</l>
               </q> The acceptable names of fathers were aptly giuen to Monkes, for they were able to tell their children both here and there in euene place. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> againſt whoredome thus writeth; <hi>Meates are ordained for the belly,<note place="margin">1 Cor 6.13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> &amp; the belly for the meates, but God ſhall deſtroye both it and them; now the bodie is not for forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the bodie: and God hath alſo raiſed vp the Lord, &amp; ſhall raiſe vs vp by his power. Know ye not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt? Shall I then take the members of Chriſt, and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid. Doo ye not know, that he which coupleth himſelfe with an harlot, is one bodie? for two (ſaith he) ſhal be one fleſh: but he that is ioyned to the Lord, is one ſpirite. Flee fornication: euerie ſinne that a man doth as without the bodie: but hee that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth fornication, ſinneth againſt his owne bodie. Know you not, that your bodie is the temple of the holy ghoſt, which is in you, Whom ye haue of God? and ye are not your owne, for ye are bought for a price: therefore glorifie God in your owne body, and in your ſpirit, for they are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15611:18"/>
            <p>Here are 7 arguments againſt whoredome:<note place="margin">7. arguments againſt whoredome.</note> the firſt is of the puniſhment in the 13. verſ. where he ſaith that <hi>meates are for the belly, &amp; the belly for meates, but God will deſtroy both it and them;</hi> for gluttonie and drunkennes are maintainers of venerie: the ſecond argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is drawen from the condition of our bodies, in the ſame verſe, <hi>the bodie is not for fornication, but for the Lord;</hi> for as God is worſhipped in heauen of angels which are ſpirites, ſo will he be worſhipped in earth of men which haue bodies; and therefore our bodies ſhall be raiſed vp to glorie: the third argument is drawen from an abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; It is againſt reaſon ſaith the apoſtle, that our bodies, being the members of Chriſt, ſhould be made the members of an harlot, &amp; ſo to bring them from high dignitie, to moſt vile indignitie: the 4. argument is drawen from the compariſon of God and an harlot; for he that ioyneth himſelfe with an harlot, is one with an harlot in affection, and ſhalbe one with an harlot in affliction; but he that coupleth himſelfe to the chaſt God, ſhall be one with God in glorie for euer: the fifth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is drawen from the effects of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, for the fornicator defileth his bodie with the pockes, leproſie, and many other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15611:18"/> loathſome diſeaſes; and therefore vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſinneth againſt his owne bodie, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his life by waſting the vigor of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. The ſixt argument is drawen from the purpoſes, whereunto the body is deſtinated; your body is the temple of the holy Ghoſt, and you are not your owne, therefore in it God muſt be worſhipped &amp; not the diuell. The ſeuenth and laſt argument is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe, in the laſt verſe; you are bought with a price, that is, not with gold nor ſiluer, but with the moſt precious blood of Chriſt; therefore not onely our ſoule muſt magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Lorde, and our ſpirit reioyce in God our Sauiour, but alſo our fleſh muſt reioyce in our God; and in the life and death of our bodies God muſt be glorified, bowing our knees to GOD the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which leadeth vs to life, and not to whores and harlottes,<note place="margin">Pro. 7.27.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe waies goe downe to hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeremies</hi> prophecie is fulfilled in them, &amp; will be fulfilled in vs;<note place="margin">Ier. 5.7.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Though I fedde them to the full, yet they committed adulterie, &amp; aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled themſelues by companies in the harlots hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: they roſe vp in the morning like fedde horſes, for euerie man neighed after his neighbours wife. Shall J not viſite theſe things ſaith the Lorde?
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15611:19"/> ſhall not my ſoule be auenged on ſuch a nation as this? climbe vpon their walles and deſtroy them, take awaie their battlements, for they are not the Lordes.</hi> The harlot calleth her pleaſure ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and ſo do our delicate dames of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: but <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſaith, this ſweete ſinne wil haue ſoure ſauce. For it will cauſe the walles of our Cities to be raſed, &amp; the battlements of our houſe to be beaten downe. God bee mercifull vnto this pleaſant Iland &amp; bleſſe it: for if euerie houſe of our lande ſhall bee deſtroyed, where this loathſome ſinne of leacherie hath bene ſhamefully committed (as the monkes houſes were) our faireſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (no doubt) will come to ruinous heapes.</p>
            <p>GOD brought the Sodomites into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, to ſhewe them, that he did hate their ſinne, yet would they not repent; GOD brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of ſlauerie by <hi>Abraham,</hi> to teach them that he was mercifull to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, yet would they not repent. We haue bene vnder the tyrant of Spaine in the late dayes of Queene <hi>Marie,</hi> yet we forſake not our former fornications: we haue bene deliuered by her Maieſtie, yet we runne on deſperately into all manner of abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, forgetting the greefe of our calamitie, and the comfort of our deliuerance, the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15611:19"/> of our priuate eſtate, the peace of our kingdome, or the felicitie which we haue by the word of God.</p>
            <p>Oppreſſion of the poore is another ſinne that prouoketh GOD to plague vs.<note place="margin">Oppresſion of the poore cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. Exo. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>J haue ſurely ſeene the affliction of my people which are in Egypt, &amp; haue heard their crie becauſe of their taskmaſters, for J know their ſorrowes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Do not the rich oppreſſe you by tyrannie, and draw you before iudgement ſeates?</hi> who oppreſſeth? <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> the tyrant, <hi>Nimrod</hi> the mightie, and <hi>Nabal</hi> the rich. Thoſe that ſhould giue do take awaie; thoſe that ſhould feede, do fleeſe; thoſe that ſhould be mercifull, be vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Whome do they oppreſſe? their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their owne fleſh, the Lords brother, and the Lords apple of his eye. And what brother? his poore, needie, deſtitute, and afflicted brother; and to whome he ſhould giue, from him he doth take by violence; &amp; whom he ſhuld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, him he doth ſpoile. How doth he oppreſſe? by his mony &amp; his might. God hath giuen them riches and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, to defend the poore &amp; fatherleſſe, to ſee ſuch as be in neede and neceſſitie to haue right; and with their wealth and might they oppreſſe &amp; deceiue, they grind the face of the poore, and braye them as it were in a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15611:20"/> morter:<note place="margin">Ier. 5.</note> their <hi>houſes are full of riches gotten by deceipt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When do they oppreſſe? in the time of the Goſpel. <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid vnto his man when he had taken gold and garments of <hi>Naaman;</hi> is <hi>this a time to take mony &amp; to receiue garments, and oliues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.26.</note> 
               <hi>and vineyardes, and ſheepe, and Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and men ſeruants, and mayd ſervants?</hi> So ſay I to the Nimrodical oppreſſors of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is this a day of peace and of ioy? is this a time to ſmite downe the people of the Lord, &amp; to murther his heritage? and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour widowes houſes, &amp; to eate vp the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like bred?<note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>While we haue time, we ſhould do good to all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>eſpecially to the houſhold of faith;</hi> &amp; in this time we do ill. <hi>This is the day of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> &amp; we make it the day of our deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.2.</note> This is <hi>the time accepted;</hi> and we by our oppreſſion of the poore will turne it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of vengeance.<note place="margin">Syr. 10.8.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing, wrong, blaſphemies, and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, a realme ſhall be tranſlated from one peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to an other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is this oppreſſion? in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate. <hi>How is the faithfull Citie become an harlot?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.21. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>it was full of iudgement, iuſtice lodged therein, but now they are murtherers: thy ſiluer is become droſſe; thy wine is mixt with water,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15611:20"/> thy Princes ore rebellious and companions of theeues: euerie one loueth giftes and followeth after rewardes; they iudge not the fatherleſſe, neither doth the widowes cauſe come before them. They turne iudgement into wormwood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; leaue off righteouſneſſe in the earth.</hi> What abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinne is this, that thoſe who <hi>ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the poore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.3.</note> 
               <hi>and ſee that ſuch as bee in neede and neceſſitie haue right,</hi> do adde affliction to the afflicted?<note place="margin">Iob. 24.15.</note> that thoſe who <hi>ſhould be eyes to the blinde,</hi> do pull out their eyes? and thoſe that <hi>ſhould be a legge to the lame,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 29.15.</note> do breake his bones in peeces? and thoſe that ſhould pull the ſpoile out of the iawes of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, commit violence, robery &amp; murther themſelues? and thoſe that ſhould giue the pure ſiluer of righteouſneſſe, giue the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthen of oppreſſion? and they that ſhould giue the wine of comfort, giue the water of teares? and they that ſhould mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter iudgement, giue the wormewood of affliction? and they that ſhould be the ſtaffe of the poore mans eſtate, are an yorne rodde to bruſe them in peeces: being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from fathers to tyraunts, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrates to theeues, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudges to murtherers, from Princes to Lyons, from Gods to diuels. For the couetous oppreſſor whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould giue,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15611:21"/> hee ſaith it is too much; when he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, he ſaith it is too little; when he ſhould forgiue, hee ſaith it is too great; when hee ſhould repent, he ſaith it is too ſoone; when he ſhould come to heare the worde of God, he ſaith it is too farre: and thus as he holdeth his needie brother vnder his yoake, ſo the diuell holdeth him faſt in his ſnare, that hee ſhall neuer eſcape, but ſhal haue iudgement without mercie, becauſe he hath ſhewed no mercie.<note place="margin">Eſay. 10, 1.</note> So true is the prophecie of <hi>Eſay, Woe be vnto you that make vnrighteous lawes, to robbe the widowes and the fatherleſſe.</hi> For as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal, 32, 1.</note> 
               <hi>God ſtandeth in the congregation of Princes, he is a iudge amongſt Gods.</hi> And therefore albeit God in his ſecret iudgement, doth ſuffer the greate &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie oppreſſors to go on in their vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealings, yet in the ende he will bring them to iudgement, and then (as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith) he <hi>will ſet in order all their ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 50.</note> I might heere ſpeak the like of murmuring &amp; rebellion, which are ſinnes that prouoke the wrath of God; but time will not giue mee leaue.</p>
            <p>I will now go to the ſinne of all ſinnes, which no doubt will procure to this lande a generall, fearefull, and ſeuere deſtruction:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15611:21"/> this ſinne is Atheiſme.<note place="margin">Atheiſme a manifeſt ſinne that crieth for ſpeedie ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</note> The Idolator is a breaker of the ſecond precept, the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the third, the prophaner of the ſaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth is a tranſgreſſour of the fourth, the rebel of the fifth, the oppreſſor of the ſixt, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domite of the ſeauenth; but the Athieſt is a wilfull contemner of all. For he denieth GOD the father, he trampleth vnder his foote the blood of our Sauiour, he diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth the ſpirit of grace; in his heart he is an infidell, in his tongue a blaſphemer, to his Prince a traytor, to his countrey a rebell, to his houſe a poyſon, to his friends a plague: whereſoeuer he goeth, the earth is accurſed; whereſoeuer he ſpeaketh, the aire is infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and whereſoeuer hee dwelleth, there dwelleth the wrath of God for euer.</p>
            <p>The ſtarre confeſſed the ſon of God, for <hi>it ledde the wiſe men to Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.10. Mat. 8.27. Mat. 21.5.</note> the <hi>ſea and the windes did obey him;</hi> the <hi>aſſe did beare him to Ieruſalem;</hi> the fiſhes obeyed him when <hi>they came into the Apoſtles nettes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.6. Mat. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. Mat. 27.51, 52.</note> ſo did the fiſh that <hi>brought mony in his mouth to paye their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute;</hi> the <hi>Sunne at his death was abaſhed, the earth did tremble, the ſtones did cleaue aſunder, and the graues did open:</hi> but our Atheiſts, more inſenſible then the ſtone or ſtarres, more hard harted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the flints, more ſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15611:22"/> then any carcaſſe, do not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Chriſt to be the ſon of God. Naye the very diuelles confeſſe Chriſt to be the Sonne of God.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>what haue I to do with thee Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the moſt high God?</hi> and <hi>Jeſus J knowe, and Paule I knowe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.15.</note> ſaith the deuill. But our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtes worſe then the deuill in this reſpect, haue ſo hardened their heart, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Ieſus to be the ſonne of God: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſith they will not acknowledge him to be a Sauiour, they ſhall know him to bee a iudge, whoſe power they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not reſiſt, whoſe wiſdome they cannot deceiue, whoſe iuſtice they cannot corrupt, and therefore will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them without reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was an idolater, but he repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: <hi>Paul</hi> was a blaſphemer, but yet hee was made a Preacher: <hi>Lew</hi> was a Publicane, but yet he became an Euangeliſt: <hi>Peter</hi> did forſweare his maſter, but yet he continued an apoſtle: <hi>Dauid</hi> was an adulterer, and yet a Prophet: <hi>Zache</hi> was an oppreſſor, but yet he was conuerted and ſaid:<note place="margin">Luke. 19.8.</note> 
               <hi>Behold Lord the one halfe of my goodes I giue to the poore, and if I haue taken from any man by forged cauillation, I reſtore him foure fold. Zache</hi> did giue the halfe of his goodes, wee will not giue the hundred part: <hi>Zache</hi> gaue of his owne, wee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15611:22"/> will not giue of that we haue wrongfullie gotten: <hi>Zache</hi> gaue his goodes, we giue of the worſt things we haue: <hi>Zache</hi> gaue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, we deferre till we be ſicke or dead. Thus we ſee that Idolaters, blaſphemers, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners &amp; adulterers, haue turned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto the Lord, but no Atheiſt: for they go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſe to worſe, they go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin to ſin, they neuer come into the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, they are veſſelles of diſhonor, they are <hi>cloudes without water carried about of windes, corrupt trees, and without frute,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>twiſe dead, and plucked vp by the rootes, they are the raging waues of the ſea, foming out their owne ſhame, they are wandering Stars, to whom is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the blackneſſe of darkeneſſe for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt thoſe therefore we muſt pray,<note place="margin">Pſa. 109.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13 14, 15. A praier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtes.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> did againſt them in his time, <hi>When he ſhall be iudged let him be condemned, and let his praier be turned into ſin: let his dayes be few, and let another take his charge, let his children be fatherleſſe, and his wife a widow, let his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be vagabonds, &amp; beg and ſeeke bread, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of their places deſtroied: let the extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner catch all that he hath, &amp; let the ſtranger ſpoile his labour: let there be none to extend mercie vnto him, neither let there be any to ſhew mercy vpon his fatherleſſe children, let his poſteritie bee
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15611:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15611:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15611:24"/> deſtroyed, &amp; in the generation following let their name be put out, let the iniquitie of his fathers bee had in remembrance with the Lord, and let not the ſinne of his mother be done awaie, but let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaie bee before the Lord, that hee may cutte off their memoriall from the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As poiſon when it entreth into the body, it infecteth firſt the vains, ſecondly the blood, thirdly, the members, &amp; laſt of al the heart: ſo Atheiſme bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the vains of the lighter ſort of people, and from thence it hath crept into the blood &amp; generoſitie of this land, by meanes whereof it is ſpread into all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and parts of this realme: God keepe it from the heart, that is, from the Court &amp; the Citie of London. If my fleſh were of ſtone, if I had the learned tongue of <hi>Eſay,</hi> or my face were of Adamant as <hi>Ezechias</hi> was, if I had that ſpirit of fortitude, which was in <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> or that bold ſpirit that was in <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> if my bones were of braſſe, and my ſides of ſteddie ſteele:<note place="margin">Mat. 14.4.</note> then as <hi>John</hi> ſaid to <hi>Herod: Jt is not lawfull for thee to haue thy brothers wife.</hi> And as <hi>Elias</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ahab:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art he that troubleth all Iſrael:</hi> ſo I ſhould ſay to our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, it is not lawful for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eate, drinke, liue or breath among chriſtians, for they are the cauſe that this land wil be brought to an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15611:24"/> euerlaſting deſtruction. My heart tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth, and my eyes ſhed teares to ſee the faintneſſe of my ſelfe and my bretheren, that this ſinne of Atheiſme openly committed is not open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproued, that others may feare. We ſhal ſay in time to come as the Prophet ſaid:<note place="margin">Eſay, 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be vnto me becauſe J held my peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the ſinnes of Sodome are euident,<note place="margin">In Sodome were many ſinnes and ſo there are in Englande. Exo, 19, 4, 9.</note> ſo are they many: <hi>Behold this was the iniquitie of thy ſiſter Sodome, pride, fulnes of bread, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of Idlenes, neither did ſhe ſtrengthen the hand of the poore and needie.</hi> Pride is of 2. ſorts, carnal and ſpirituall: carnall pride is that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the decking &amp; trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the fleſh, againſt which <hi>Paul</hi> thus writeth:<note place="margin">Rom, 13, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Take no thought of the fleſh to fulfil the luſtes of it.</hi> And women are forbidden to weare <hi>broidred haire, or gold, or pearles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim, 2, 9. 1, Pet, 3, 3.</note> 
               <hi>or coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparell.</hi> And the like is alſo inhibited by Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> This pride was in the harlot,<note place="margin">Prou, 7, 16, 17.</note> who ſaid: ſhe had <hi>deckt her bed with couerings and clothes of Egipt, and made her hed to ſmell of mirrhe, Aloes, &amp; Cynamon.</hi> And this pride Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reproueth, when hee willeth vs not to <hi>faſhion our ſelues according to this world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 12, 2.</note> But notwithſtanding, pride is firſt in al ages, as in children, yong and old. Secondly, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſexe, as in men and women. Thirdly,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15611:25"/> in all eſtates, as in magiſtrats &amp; priuate men. Fourthly, in all times, as in poperie, and in the Goſpell. Fiftly, in all places, as in the market and in the temple.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Apparel was ordained for three cauſes.</note>Apparell was giuen for three ends: for honeſties ſake to couer our vnſeemly parts: for necesſities ſake, to defend vs from the iniurie of the weather: and for dignities ſake both to diſtinguiſh men from beaſts, &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of high degree from the lower ſort. GOD clothed the noble ſubiect of the ſoule with <hi>a vile bodie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> to teach vs that we ſhould not deck our vile bodie with gorgeous apparell, not agreeing either with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lines, neceſſitie, or our calling.<note place="margin">Ciprian.</note> I thinke it good (ſaith <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>) that not onely maides and widowes, but alſo married women be warned, that they ſhould by no meanes adulterate the worke of God,<note place="margin">Ierom.</note> and his making: for as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaith: Theſe things are the nouriſhments of luſt, and the tokens of an vnchaſt minde: How can ſhe weepe for her ſinnes, or lift vp her eies and countenance to heauen, whome God doth not know? <hi>Thomas</hi> deceiued <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> by trimming of apparell, <hi>Iezabell</hi> pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her face to deceiue <hi>Ieho, Cleopatra</hi> pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her face to deceiue <hi>Antonius,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome of <hi>Octauian,</hi> he killed hir
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15611:25"/> himſelfe and buried her aliue with an aſpe in the ſepulcher of <hi>Antonius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Hexameron ſaith,<note place="margin">Ambr. in hex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amer.</note> do not take awaie the picture of God, and take on thee the picture of an harlot, for that picture doth not become thee, but is faultie, not of ſimplicitie but of deceipt, it beguileth and deceiueth: ſo that thou canſt not pleaſe him whom thou deſireſt to pleaſe, which vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth that it is not his but an other mans that pleaſeth,and thou deſpiſeſt thy maker, whoſe workmanſhip is defaced.</q> For as <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> noteth:<note place="margin">Ierom.</note> 
               <q>If a woman decke her ſelfe that ſhe may prouoke the lookes of men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, although there follow no harme, yet she ſhall ſuffer eternall condemnation, for ſhe hath offered poyſon, if any wil drinke of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alas, alas, that greate citie that was clothed in fine linnen, and purple, &amp; ſcarlet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 18.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; gilt with gold, and pretious ſtones, and pearles: for in one houre ſo greate riches are come to deſolation.</hi> Here yee ſee that pride goeth before, and deſtruction commeth after. So the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſheweth how this pride is puniſhed with a generall &amp; ſeuere deſolation:<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.19.17.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe (ſaith he) the daughters of Sion are hawtie and walke with ſtretched out neckes and wandering
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15611:26"/> eyes, walking and minſing as they goe, &amp; making a tinckling with their feete, therefore ſhall the Lord make the heades of the daughters of Sion bald, &amp; the Lord ſhal diſcouer their ſecret partes: in that day ſhall the Lorde take awaie the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſlippers, &amp; of the calles &amp; the rounde tires, the ſweete balles and the bracelets, and the bonnets, the tires of the heades, and the ſloppes &amp; the head-bandes, and the tablets, &amp; the earings, and the mufflers, the coſtly apparell, and the vailes, the wimples, and the criſping pinnes, all the glaſſes, and the fine linnen, &amp; the hoodes, &amp; the launes: and in ſteed of ſweete ſauors there ſhall be ſtinke, &amp; in ſteede of a girdle a rent, and in ſteed of dresſing the haire, baldneſſe, &amp; in ſteed of a ſtomacher, a girding of ſackclothe, &amp; burning in ſtede of beautie: thy men ſhal fall by the ſword, and thy ſtrength in the battell. Then ſhall her gates mourne and lament, and ſhee being deſolate ſhall ſitte on the grounde.</hi> Carnall pride is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned but a ſmall fault, but yet as yee do wel ſee, and learne out of the holy Sciptures, it bringeth ſword, mourning, and vtter deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>But conſider I pray you the courſe of this world: Chriſt ſaith, wee ſhould take no thought for apparell, &amp; all our delight is to go braue: the Iſralites did weare their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15611:26"/> fortie yeares, &amp; we muſt change our apparel euery tearme: Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded his Diſciples they ſhuld haue but one coate, &amp; we muſt haue for euery day in the weeke a coate <hi>Jho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt</hi> was clothed in a Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>els skin, but we muſt be clothed (with <hi>Diues</hi>)in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; fine white, &amp; with <hi>Herod</hi> we muſt be attired in gorgeous apparel, &amp; therfore with <hi>Diues</hi> &amp; <hi>Herod</hi> we ſhal ſuffer a ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fusio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> ſaid:<note place="margin">Heſt. 14.16.</note> 
               <hi>Thou knoweſt O Lord that I hate the token of my preheminence &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which I beare vpon my head, what time I muſt ſhew myſelfe and be ſeene, and that I abhorre it as vncleane cloth, and that I weare it not when J am quiet and alone by my ſelfe.</hi> As this good Queene did abhorre pride in apparel, ſo the daughters of vanitie now adaies do highly eſteeme it: But as in a coffin when it is moſt ſumptuouſly dect there is (no doubt) a dead carkas there lying: ſo where yee ſee the daughters of men to haue their broidred haire, their gold and pearles, contrarie to the <hi>rule of the Apoſtle:</hi> there (no doubt) is a dead ſtinking ſoule. <hi>Democrates</hi> ſaid: There were two ornaments of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> few wordes, and few garments. The woman of Lacidemon refuſed pretious garments ſent them by <hi>Dioniſius:</hi> the Roman matrons ſent
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15611:27"/> backe againe golden roabes giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> freely by <hi>Pyrrhus.</hi> I wil end therfore with an hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Bactrians, whoſe wiues fell from the pride of apparell to whoredome, not onely with their ſeruantes, but with ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: and they gat ſuch a maſterie, and rule ouer their husbands, that albeit their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands did ſee them committing adulterie, yet they durſt not reproue them.</p>
            <p>But as I would haue the dames of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to leaue wanton and ſuperfluous appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, ſo I will with <hi>Tertulian</hi> commend vnto them a good ſute of raiment, <q>Come forth (ſaith <hi>Tertulian</hi>) yee women beutified with the ornaments of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Tertulian.</note> hauing the whiteneſſe of ſimplicitie, the redneſſe of chaſtitie, hauing your eyes painted with ſhamefaſtneſſe, and your ſpirites with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, hauing in your eares the word of God, and tying to your neckes the yoke of Chriſt, ſubiect your head to your husbands and you ſhall be braue inough, occupie your hands with wool, faſten your feete at home, and you ſhall pleaſe more, then if you were clad in golde: decke our ſelfe with the ſilke of ſinceritie, with the Satten of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and with the purple of probitie, &amp; you ſhall haue God to be your paramour:</q> Thus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15611:27"/> farre of carnall pride.</p>
            <p>Spirituall pride is of foure ſortes, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemye, arrogancie, vaineglorye, and ſelfe-loue. In blaſphemie offended <hi>Nabuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar: Is not this great Babel which J haue built for the houſe of my kingdome by the might of my power, and for the honour of my maieſtie?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4, 27, Blaſphemie the ſin of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and England.</note> Such Babilonian blaſphemers haue we in England. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Euerye good gift and euerye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift commeth from aboue from the father of lightes:</hi> but the blaſphemer thinketh his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to come from fortune, and corporall giftes to come from nature, and giftes of the minde to come by ſtudy and experience. Therefore as <hi>Nabuchadnezer</hi> was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a beaſt, vntill hee did acknowledge theſe thinges to come from God: ſo all they that call their gorgeous houſes their owne, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezar</hi> did: or do ſay, their barneful of corne is for themſelues, <hi>as the rich man did:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12. Exod. 14. Num. 16.</note> or boaſt of their armies, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did: or bragge of their holyneſſe, as <hi>Dathan</hi> did: or doe pride themſelues in their kinglye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as <hi>Saul</hi> did: or of their tirannye,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 1. King. 12. Eſay 37. Iud. 6.15. Heſt. 4. Acts. 12.</note> as <hi>Roboam</hi> did: or of their victories, as <hi>Sana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib</hi> did: or of their proweſſe, as <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes</hi> did: or of their witte, as <hi>Aman</hi> did: or of their eloquence, as <hi>Herod</hi> did:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15611:28"/> or of their ſtocke,<note place="margin">Iohn 9.</note> as <hi>the Jewes did:</hi> Theſe all haue the pride of Sodome, and ſhall haue the puniſhment of Sodome vnleſſe they repent.</p>
            <p>Arrogancie is another ſinne of Sodome fallen,<note place="margin">Arrogancye the ſinne of Sodome and of England.</note> and of England falling: and that is, when we confeſſe wee haue receiued all good giftes from God: but wee ſaye wee haue merited them. Which ſinne Saint <hi>Paul</hi> eftſoones reprooueth:<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>By grace are yee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that of faith, and that not of your ſelues. It is the gifte of GOD, not of workes, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe.</hi> If wee bee not ſaued of our ſelues, nor of workes, how is it true that wee bee ſaued by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites? <hi>Aquinas</hi> bringeth manye reaſons to prooue that wee are not ſaued by workes, which neither the Seminaryes which come from Rheimes, nor the Ieſuits which come from Rome can confute.<note place="margin">7. Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt merits out of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</note> The firſt is, the indignitye of our merites: <hi>For J counte</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthie of the glorye which ſhall bee ſhewed vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18,</note> Secondlye, wee can not merite, by reaſon of the contrarietye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the bodye and the ſoule: <hi>For the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe, 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſpirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſhe:</hi> and theſe are contrarye
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15611:28"/> one to another, ſo that yee cannot doe theſe thinges as yee would. The third reaſon why wee cannot merite, is becauſe of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the fleſhe.<note place="margin">Sap. 9.15.</note> For <hi>the corruptible bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye is a burthen vnto the ſoule, and the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye habitation preſſeth downe the minde full of cares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth reaſon why we cannot merit, is the ſtraitnes of the waye.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>Enter in at the ſtrait gate, for it is the broad gate and wide way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there bee which goe in thereat, becauſe the gate is ſtraite, and the way narrowe that leadeth vnto life, and fewe there be that finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth reaſon why we cannot merit, is becauſe of the difficulty of good workes, for vertue is occupied about that which is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culte. For it is an hard thing to beleeue, but it is eaſie to preſume or diſpaire: it is hard to be liberal, but it is eaſie to be couetous, or prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall: it is hard to be valiant, but it is eaſie to be raſh or timerous.</p>
            <p>The ſixth reaſon why we cannot merite, is the incertitude of our owne righteouſnes: <hi>We haue all bene</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay) as an vnclean thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 69.6.</note> 
               <hi>and all our righteouſnes is as filthy cloutes:</hi> for our righteouſneſſe is neither pure, perfect, nor perpetuall.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:15611:29"/>
            <p>The ſeauenth and the laſt reaſon is, the ſtraitneſſe of the Iudge:<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.2.</note> 
               <hi>Enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) for in thy ſight ſhall no man liuing bee iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> If <hi>Dauid</hi> cannot bee iuſtified in the ſight of GOD, neither can the proude Phariſey, ſaucye Sadducey, or popiſh Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian.</p>
            <p>Such arrogant Papiſtes are well tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to bee full of winde: For as the winde firſt diſtinguiſheth the light, ſecondly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the dewe, and thirdly bloweth vp the duſt: ſo this vaunting of merites darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the pure light of Gods glorye, it dryeth vp the dewe of his grace in them and ſo puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth them vp with a ſwelling conceite of their owne holyneſſe, that they attribute that to nature which is due to grace, and that to merite which is due to the promiſe, and that to the fleſhe which is due to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and that to works which is due to faith, and that to the Lawe which is due to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: and finally that to man which is due to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vaine glory the ſin of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and of England. Apoc. 3, 16, 17.</note>Vaineglorye is another kinde of pride: this was in the Church of Laodicia: <hi>Thou ſayeſt J am riche, and encreaſed with goods, and haue neede of nothing, and knoweſt not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15611:29"/> how thou art wretched and miſerable, and poore, and blinde and naked.</hi> This vaineglory was in <hi>Alexander,</hi> whome paraſites had perſwaded that hee was a God: but in the end when he perceiued hee muſt dye, hee vttered theſe woordes: Now I perceiue I am but a mortal man. <hi>Let vs not be deſirous of vaineglory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 6.26.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle. We cannot glory of things paſt, for in times paſt wee haue committed more offences then good deedes: wee cannot glorye of thinges preſent, becauſe wee are in exile: wee cannot glorye of thinges to come, becauſe there is comming, death and iudgement.</p>
            <p>Vaineglorye is hardlye ſhunned for three cauſes: firſt becauſe it ariſeth of well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, euen as the moth is bred in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when it conſumeth, and the worme in the wood which it rotteth. Secondly, al other vices are ouercome of ſome vertue: as adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery by chaſtitye, couetouſneſſe by merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hatred by loue: but vaineglorye ariſeth of well doing. Thirdly, by how much the more vainglory is kept down, by ſo much the more it is encreaſed. For euerye euill ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of an euill, but onely vaineglory procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of well doing.</p>
            <p>Praiſe is deſired ordinatly or inordinatly: or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15611:30"/> for the glory of God:<note place="margin">Mat, 5, 16.</note> 
               <hi>But let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good woorkes, and glorifye your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heauen.</hi> And ſecondlye, for the profite of our Neighbour, <hi>procure thinges honeſt in the ſight of all men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.17. 1. Cor. 10.33.</note> 
               <hi>I pleaſe all men in all thinges, not ſeeking myne owne profite, but the profit of many, that they might be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inordinatly, men ſeeke praiſe: firſt, when they deſire to bee praiſed for thoſe thinges that be not worthye of praiſe, as for riches and temporall thinges which are but vaine. Secondly, if they glorye in their ſinnes: <hi>why boaſteſt thou O tyrant, that thou art able to doe miſcheefe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.8.</note> Thirdlye, when it is doone in contempt of our neighbour, or of God. <hi>For they loued the prayſe of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 12.43.</note> 
               <hi>more then the praiſe of God. Now vnto tht King euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>immortall, inuiſible, vnto God onelye wiſe, bee honour and glorye for euer and euer, Amen.</hi> Fourthlye, when a man ſinneth to get praiſe:<note place="margin">Mat. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Beware that yee giue not your almes before men to bee ſeene of them, or elſe you ſhall haue no rewarde of your Father which is in Heauen.</hi> How manye vaineglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons are in England, which boaſt of the multitude of their riches, reioyce in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15611:30"/> iniquitie, and loue the praiſe of men more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glory of God: you may know by <hi>Catoes</hi> rule for he ſaith: Neither ſhalt thou praiſe nor diſpraiſe thy ſelfe, for this doe fooles that are vexed with vaineglory. If all thoſe that praiſe themſelues be fooles, then the world is full of fooles, and theſe ſay there is no GOD: <hi>But hee that ſitteth in heauen will laugh them to ſcorne, yea,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> the Lord will haue them in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An other kinde of pride is ſelfe-loue,<note place="margin">Self-loue the ſin of Sodom and of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Mal, 2, 10.</note> of the which <hi>Malachie</hi> writeth: <hi>Haue wee not all one Father? hath not one God made vs? why doe wee tranſgreſſe euerye one againſt his Brother?</hi> This vice was in the Phariſey:<note place="margin">Luke 18.11.</note> 
               <hi>J am not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>as other men are, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, vniuſt, adulterers, nor as this Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane. When Saul was little in his owne ſight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam, 15, 17</note> 
               <hi>hee was the head of the trybes of Iſraell.</hi> But when hee deſpiſed <hi>Dauid,</hi> a better man then himſelfe, God brought him low againe. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> humbled himſelfe, and ſaide:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> Hee was not <hi>worthye to vnlooſe the latchet of our Sauiours ſhooe:</hi> But Chriſt ſaide: <hi>Hee was a Prophet, and more then a Prophet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.11. Iohn 8, 33.</note> The Iewes ſaide, that they <hi>were the children of Abraham, and neuer ſerued any man.</hi> But Chriſt ſaide,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8, 44.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are of your Father
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15611:31"/> the Diuell.</hi> Wee may not therefore with the Phariſies iudge others and preferre our ſelues before them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fiue reaſons why we may not ivdge our brethren.</note>For firſt humanitie doth require that we ſhould not raſhly cenſure the faults of other men. Secondly, our owne infirmitye ſhould moue vs to the ſame,<note place="margin">Iam, 3, 2,</note> for <hi>in many thinges we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all.</hi> Now doe wee ſee our owne faultes, which are in the peece of the wallet that han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth behinde vs. Thirdly, we are fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and being therfore in the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee ſhould liue in charitie which coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the multitude of ſinnes. Fourthly, Chriſt is the onely iudge of the quicke and the dead, and therefore we may not male partly aſcend into his tribunall ſeate. Fifthlye, our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are to be ſuſpected, becauſe we ſee only the outward and not the inward partes.<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Baſill</hi> ſaith: The wicked man doth moſt eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the good, but the good doth not eaſily condemne the wicked. Moſt iuſtly therefore ſaith the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Rom, 14, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Who art thou that miſdeemeſt an other mans ſeruant? hee ſtandeth or falleth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Lord. Saul</hi> breathing out miſcheefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the church of God, was ſuddenly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and of <hi>Saul</hi> became <hi>Paul,</hi> of a proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie an humble penitent, of a malicious perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor a zealous Apoſtle, and laboured more
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15611:31"/> in his vocation then all his fellowes.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Au. de verb. dom. ſer. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> we muſt deſpaire of none as long as the patience of God doth lead him to repentance, neither he, that will not haue the death of a ſinner, but that he ſhould turn and liue, doth take him out of this life. He is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to day, how knoweſt thou but he may be a Chriſtian to morrow? he is an vnbeleeuing Iew to day, what if to morrow he attaine to the Catholique religion? he is a Schiſmatique to day, what if to morrowe hee embrace the vnitie of the Church? what if thoſe in whom you finde all kinde of error and condemne as moſt deſperate, ſhall repent before they ende their life? Therefore brethren, this doth the Apoſtle warne you, iudge not any man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time come.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This rule of the Apoſtle as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, condemneth the Phariſies that were in Chriſtes time, the Catharoi that were in <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time, the Donatiſtes that were in <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> time, and the Martiniſtes of our time. They haue written a booke of Martin mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate, I hope hereafter they wil write a book of Martin marphariſey.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noteth in a Treatiſe hee hath of the conflict of vertues and vices,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> ſelfe-loue giueth vs this counſell, thou art
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15611:32"/> better then all others in eloquence, riches, and honours, and in all giftes both ſpirituall and corporall, deſpiſe therefore all and make thy ſelfe better then all: ſo ſaith Martin, that hee is better then the Biſhops and Miniſters of this land.</p>
            <p>So ſayde the falſe Prophettes in <hi>Eſayes</hi> time.<note place="margin">Eſay 65, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Stand aparte, come not neere, for I am holyer then thou.</hi> But albeit Martin hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny followers, which hope by ſacriledge to enriche themſelues; yet let them hearken what God ſpeaketh by the mouth of his Prophet:<note place="margin">Ier. 2.35.</note> 
               <hi>Beholde, J will enter into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thee, becauſe thou ſayeſt I haue not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> when hee perſwaded the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to rebellyon, ſayde, <hi>Oh that I were made iudge in the land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Sam. 15.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>that euery man which hath anye matter in controuerſye might come to mee, that J might doe him iuſtice, and when any man came neere to him and did him obeyſance, hee put forth his hand and tooke him and kiſſed him: and that hee ſtole the harts of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Abſolom</hi> made the people beleeue hee would doe iuſtice better then <hi>Dauid:</hi> ſo doth Martine make the Worlde beleeue, that he will miniſter diſcipline a great deale
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15611:32"/> better then the graue fathers of this land; and to this end he bendeth himſelfe to driue our Biſhops out of their houſes, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> did his father. But I pray God giue them grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the tragical end of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> that ſo they by repentance may eſcape the like. For otherwiſe God will be auenged of the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; ſlaunders that haue bene vſed againſt Miniſters and Prophets.<note place="margin">Zach, 2, 8.</note> 
               <hi>For hee that toucheth you</hi> (ſaith God to his prophets) <hi>toucheth the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of my eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fulneſſe of bread is another ſinne that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runneth our ouerthrow,<note place="margin">Fulneſſe of bread, the ſinne of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and of England. Eccl. 2, 4, &amp;c.</note> for fulneſſe of bread cauſeth curioſitie. For then we <hi>make vs great workes, builde vs houſes, plant vineyardes, make vs gardens, and plant in them all maner of trees; then we make ceſternes of water, to water therewith the woods that growe; then we get vs ſeruants and maides, poſſeſsion of beeues and ſheepe; then we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp ſiluer and golde, and the cheefe treaſures of Kings; then we prouide vs men ſingers and maide ſingers, and the delightes of the ſonnes of men.</hi> As fulneſſe of bread cauſeth curioſitie, ſo curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie cauſeth pleaſure:<note place="margin">Amos 6, 3, &amp;c</note> ſo that the wicked <hi>Put farre away the euill day, acd approche to the ſeate of iniquitie, they lye vpon beds of iuory, and ſtretch themſelues vpon their beds, and eate the Lambes of the flocke, and the Calues out of the ſtall, they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15611:33"/> ſing to the ſound of the viole, they inuent to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues inſtrumentes of muſicke like Dauid; they drinke wine in bowles, and annointe themſelues with ſweete oyntements, and no man is ſory for the affliction of Ioſeph.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Tim, 3.4.</note> And as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>They are lovers of pleaſure, more then louers of God.</hi> As fulneſſe of bread cauſeth curioſitie: and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie pleaſure: ſo pleaſure is the cauſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.<note place="margin">Pſal, 10.41 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked is ſo proud hee careth not for God, neither is God in all his thoughtes, his waies are alwaies proſperous, therefore defyeth he all his enemies, for hee ſaith in his hart, J ſhall neuer be moued, there ſhall no harme happen vnto me:</hi> and againe a little after,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>God hath forgotten, hee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth away his face, and will neuer ſee it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the eſtate of the Sodomites, to put far from them the euil day, to giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (as Chriſt ſaith) to eating, drinking, building, planting, and to voluptuouſneſſe, to ſaye they ſhould neuer be moued nor be in danger: to truſt to their riches which were <hi>vncertaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Tim, 6, 17. Pſal, 46, 19.</note> to their Caſtles which were rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous: to their bow which was <hi>broken:</hi> to their ſpeare which was <hi>knapt a ſunder:</hi> to their horſe which was but vaine: to their hoſtes of men, which were but <hi>Graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 40.</note> to their Captaines which were but Locuſtes: to their Princes, which are <hi>but mortall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 46.</note> to their counſels which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15611:33"/> are of <hi>none effect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 33.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What is the cauſe that the tyrantes of the earth forget the fall of <hi>Pharaoh?</hi> fulneſſe of bread. What is the cauſe the idolatrous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes of England remember not the <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death of the idolaters?</hi> fulneſſe of bread.<note place="margin">Exo, 32.28.</note> What is the cauſe that murmurers of our time, forget the fearfull deſtruction of the <hi>murmuring Jewes?</hi> fulneſſe of bread.<note place="margin">Num, 26, 65.</note> What is the cauſe that fornicators remember not the ſlaughter of the <hi>twentie and foure thouſand?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num, 24, 9.</note> fulneſſe of bread hath ſet this iudgement out of their ſight. Why doe wee caſt out of our remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the drowning of the whole Worlde? which was ſo generall, that a <hi>doue could not pitch her foote on any ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 8, 9,</note> fulneſſe of bread hath ſet this iudgement of GOD out of our ſight. Why doe wee forget So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorrha (of the which not only <hi>Moſes</hi> hath written, but <hi>Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Ieremie, Amos, Zephanie,</hi> all the Euangeliſtes, and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi>) which was deſtroyed with fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, in ſuch ſorte, that to this daye no graſſe can growe in it, no byrd can flye in it, no fiſh can liue in the waters of it, no cattle on the ground, nor no man in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey? fulneſſe of bread hath ſet this fearfull
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15611:34"/> iudgement declared by <hi>Moſes,</hi> repeated by the Prophets, preached by the Euangeliſtes, and inculcated by the Apoſtles, farre out of our ſight.</p>
            <p>Why doe we burye in obliuion the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Iewes, which was moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Firſt, becauſe it was in the feaſt of the Paſſe-ouer, when they were all aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together. Secondlye, becauſe of the domeſticall ſedition, for there were three Ruffians that ſtriued in the Cittie for the gouernement, <hi>John, Simon,</hi> and <hi>Eleazer,</hi> and theſe ſo skirmiſhed one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in one daye eight thouſand, and in an other daye tenne thouſande or more were ſlaine within the walles. Thirdlye, by reaſon of the plague which was ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that from the fourteenth day of Aprill, vnto the Calendes of Iuly, there dyed in the peſtilence a hundreth fifteene thouſand and eightie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by reaſon of the famine which was ſo extreame, that the husbands pulled the meate out of their wiues mouthes, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes from the children, the children from the parentes, the Brethren from the ſiſters, ſiſters from the brethren; they did eat haye,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15611:34"/> old leather pluckt off their targets, oxe dung, and pigeons dung, and a noble woman dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a ſtreet called Batezor killed her owne infant to eat it, but before ſhe killed him, ſhe vttered theſe wordes with teares, and kiſſed him ſaying; o wretched childe for whom ſhal I keepe thee in warre, famin, and ſedition? if thou goeſt to the Romans there is bondage, and before bondage goeth famine, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious wil afflict vs worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both: woe be vnto me moſt wretched mother; I did hope that thou ſhouldſt burye me, but now alas pinching famine (which pierceth my bowels and marow) forceth me that I muſt bury thee againe in my belly, whom before I haue carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my womb; and when ſhe had wept and kiſſed him often, ſhe put her child behind her and killed it with a dagger, &amp; ſaid be thou to me meat: to the ſeditious <hi>Erinnis,</hi> and to the world a fable. Fiftly, it was greeuous, becauſe two thouſand killed themſelues. Sixtlye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Senatours were put to moſt vile workes. Seuenthly, becauſe this was all done of the enemies of religion. Eghtly, becauſe it was in the time of harueſt. And laſtly, becauſe of the great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſlain, which were 110000. and of the captains which were 97000. what
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15611:35"/> maketh vs I ſay, to forget this heauie down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of the Iewes (which periſhed with famin, peſtilence, the ſword, and captiuity) but ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of bread.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> though he repented for his whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and murther, yet his puniſhment was ſo great,<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.3.</note> that hee ſaide, <hi>There is nothing ſound in my fleſhe becauſe of thy anger, neither is there reſt in my bones becauſe of my ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>I cauſe my bed euery night to ſwimme, and water my couch with teares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.10.</note> 
               <hi>My ſtrength faileth, and the light of my eyes euer is not my own.</hi> Yea his own Son <hi>Abſalom</hi> firſt draue him out of his houſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, defloured his own wiues, thirdly, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, fourthly, for one <hi>Vrias</hi> were ſlaine three of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſonnes, <hi>Ammon, Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> and <hi>Adonias.</hi> Therefore well ſaith <hi>Dauid, My fleſh trembleth for feare of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.120.</note> 
               <hi>and I am afraide of thy iudgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was afraide of Gods iudgementes, becauſe the ſworde neuer departed from his houſe; but we that liue in fulneſſe of bread; we feare not the iudgementes of God in the ſlaughter of the idolaters, the deſtruction of the murmurers, the murther of the fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the pittifull deſolation of Ieruſalem, the drowning of all the worlde, the burning
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:15611:35"/> of Sodome and Gomorrha in the vengeance of eternall fire.</p>
            <p>Wherfore it is beter to eate the bread of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and drinke the water of teares, then to haue fulneſſe of bread to fulfil the luſts of the fleſh and the meaſure of iniquitye. And <hi>better it is to goe to the houſe of mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>then to the houſe of ioy.</hi> And to this purpoſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Woe be vnto them that are full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 6.25.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall hunger; woe be vnto you that now laugh, for ye ſhall weepe and howle.</hi> For they that haue liued here in pleaſure and laughter, ſhal goe the blacke way with ſighes and teares, from God and his Angels, from ſaintes, from ioy and felicitie, to the fiends of hell, to ſuppe in the pallace of darkeneſſe, with the Princes of horror, at the table of vengeance, in the Chaire of calamitye, with the Crowne of death vpon their head; and the diuel ſhal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them vntill they crye out with <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>My puniſhment is greater, then J am able to beare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Idleneſſe is an other ſinne which crieth for vengeance, againſt which <hi>Paul</hi> thus writeth:<note place="margin">Idleneſſe the ſinne of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and of England. 2. Theſ. 6. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Wee commaund you in the name of Chriſt Ieſus, that ye withdraw your ſelues from euery Brother which walketh inordinately, and not after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution he hath receiued of vs: for ye your ſelues
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:15611:36"/> know, how yee ought to follow vs, for we beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not our ſelues inordinately amongſt you; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tooke wee bread of any man for nought, for wee wrought with labour and trauaile, night and daye, becauſe wee would not bee cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any of you: not but that wee had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but that wee might make our ſelues an enſample vnto you to followe vs. For euen vvhen vvee vvere vvith you, this vvee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you of, that if there vvere anye that vvould not worke, hee ſhould not eate. For vve heard that there were ſome amongst you vvhich walke inordinately and worke not at all, but are buſie bodies: therefore them that are ſuch, vve commaunde and exhort by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that they vvorke with quietneſſe, and eate their owne bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Paul</hi> commaundeth them not in his owne name, but by the authoritie of Chriſt, that they ſhould labour. Secondly, hee ſaith that idleneſſe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is a perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the order of God, who hath appointed euery man his perſonall vocation, wherein he muſt ſtand and labour. Thirdly, idleneſſe is contrarye to the inſtitution and doctrine of the Apoſtle. Fourthlye, hee teacheth them to labour by his owne example, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he had authoritie to reape their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:15611:36"/> thinges, becauſe he taught them ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; yet he would not be burdenous vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but got his liuing with his own hands. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſaith; That he that wil not labour, muſt not eate.<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.2.</note> 
               <hi>For every man muſt eate the labour of his owne hands.</hi> Sixtlye, idle perſons are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie bodies, being moſt peſtilent people to the Church of God. For a great parte of their life they ſpend in doing ill, a greater part in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, but the greateſt part of all in medling with that, they haue nothing to do withall.</p>
            <p>Of the idleneſſe of Miniſters, (how they <hi>ſeeke their owne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21. Phil. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>and not theſe things which are Jeſus Chriſts;</hi> whoſe <hi>end is damnation, whoſe God is their bellye, vvhoſe glorye is their ſhame, vvhich minde earthly things</hi>) Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with teares complaineth. Of the idleneſſe of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, how they lye <hi>vpon beds of iuorye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 6.4. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtretch themſelues forth on their couches, and eate the lambes out of the flocke, and the Calues out of the ſtall, and drinke wine in boules, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint themſelues with ſweet ointments:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bar. 3.17.</note> and <hi>take their paſtimes with the foules of the aire, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp ſiluer as the duſt:</hi> and <hi>care not for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of Joſeph:</hi> The prophets cry out in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place.</p>
            <p>Three great and horrible ſinnes come of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:15611:37"/> idleneſſe:<note place="margin">Three great ſinnes come of idleneſſe, murther, whordome, and theft.</note> The firſt is murther, for when <hi>Cain</hi> was idle, he killed his brother. And idleneſſe is the cauſe of ſo many fraies and bloodſheds, that are in &amp; about London. For as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith; they lye in wait, which cannot be perfourmed without idleneſſe. I would wiſh that yong Gentlemen and ſeruing men were kept from idleneſſe, and then no doubt they would keep themſelues from homicide. The ſecond ſinne that commeth from idleneſſe, is whoredome; for <hi>Dauid</hi> being idle, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſlept on his bed, luſted after <hi>Ber-ſheba.</hi> And it being demaunded why <hi>Aegiſtus</hi> was an adulterer, it is anſwered he was an idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Take away idleneſſe, and loues arts wil be at an end No maruel therfore if there be ſuch whoring in England, ſith there is abundance of idleneſſe. All our vaine Ballades and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton books whence come they but from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?<note place="margin">7. Cauſes of whordome.</note> Learned men haue noted ſeauen cauſes of whordome. Firſt, original ſin; ſecondly, the outward ſence; thirdly, the temperature of the bodie; fourthly, the diuel; fifthly, conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with women; ſixtly, idleneſſe, ſeuenth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the memory of women. The diuel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth idleneſſe, idleneſſe cauſeth vs to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber women, remembrance cauſeth concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, &amp; concupiſcence cauſeth adultery. The
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:15611:37"/> third ſinne that commeth of idlenes is theft. <hi>Enter not</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) into the way of the wicked, and walke not in the way of wicked men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 4.19. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>for they cannot ſleepe vnleſſe they haue done euill, and their ſleepe departeth except they cauſe ſome to fall; for they eate the bread of wickedneſſe, and drinke the wine of robberye.</hi> Idleneſſe cauſeth pouerty, pouerty famin, &amp; famin cauſeth rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery: &amp; therfore <hi>Solomon</hi> praieth,<note place="margin">Pro. 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Giue me not pouerty, nor riches, feed me with foode conuenient for me, leaſt J be full &amp; deny thee, &amp; ſay who is the Lord? or leaſt I be poore and ſteale, and take the name of my God in vain.</hi> Wherfore as you haue made many lawes againſt murther, whoredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and theft: ſo I pray you make ſeuere lawes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt idlenes, for al idle perſons are either bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie bodies, murderers, adulterers, or theeues. Chriſt reprouing thoſe that ſtoode idle in the market place ſaid;<note place="margin">Mat. 21.6. Rhabbanus in Mat.</note> 
               <hi>Why ſtand ye heere all day idle? Rhabbanus</hi> writing vpon this place, ſaith thus. <q>Firſt he reproueth them for the want of reaſon, ô thou ſluggard, thou deformed mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I ſpeake to thee, thou haſt the bellye of an oſtrich, the throat of a dragon, the thighes of an elephant, the feete of a cammel, the legs of an Aſſe, and the head of a Cowe: hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth doe mooue, and euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Plannettes are turned about with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:15611:38"/> their maker, the ſtarres doe ſhine, the windes doe ariſe, the riuers doe runne, the fire doth enflame, the earth doth fructifie, the trees doe budde, the birdes doe ſing, the beaſtes doe ſeeke their praie, the fiſhes doe ſearch the bottome of the Sea; all thinges doo as they bee made, onely thou remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vnmoueable, to whoſe care all things are ſubiect. Thy creator hath commaunded that whiles thou haſt time, thou ſhouldeſt worke. The Angels thy watchfull keepers inuite thee, the diuels doe mocke thee: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe therefore O ſluggard and goe to the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t and learne wiſedome of him; for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Harueſt is, hee gathereth the beſt graine and layeth them vp in his houſe, he repaireth the decayed places, that hee may exclude the Winter ſtormes. This ſommer our Harueſt is our life: the Winter ſhall be of three moneths, in the poynt of death, in the day of iudgement and in deepe hell, in all which ſhall happen fearefull tempeſtes. Ariſe therefore O ſluggard, and gather the graines of grace.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, he reproueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in regard of the neceſsitie of the place agreeing; for as in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen al men ſhal reſt, and in hell all ſuffer, ſo in earth all muſt labour.<note place="margin">Iohn 5.15.</note> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My father
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:15611:38"/> woorketh hitherto, and I woorke:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit it ſelfe maketh requeſtes for vs with ſighes that cannot bee expreſſed. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> planted a vineyard, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jaacob</hi> were ſhepheards, the iudges ſate in the gates and miniſtred iuſtice, the kings and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant captaines fought the Lords battailes, all the people of GOD in this life haue either laboured in manuall artes, or in teaching, or in gouerning, or in counſelling. For the Church is a vineyard, wherin are diggers and deluers; a Harueſt wherein are labourers; a ſhip wherein are either painfull Marriners, or fighting ſouldiers; a houſe, wherein euerye one hath his miniſterye; a bodie, wherein euery member hath his office; here therefore to ſtand idle, is a great ſhame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are reprehended in reſpect of the ſtrength of their bodies: <hi>Why ſtand ye?</hi> Impotent perſons as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, lye at the doores and cannot ſtande, therefore they are to be refreſhed by others: but thoſe that haue a ſound minde in a ſound bodie, they ought not to ſtande idle, but to walke in their vocation honeſtlye. Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding water ſoone ſtincketh, ſo idle perſons are an abhomination to the Lord: Iron that lyeth ſtill, ruſteth; ſo idle perſons giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:15611:39"/> either to murder, whordome or theft. Therefore as an idoll is a vaine and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thing, which hath eies &amp; yet ſeeth not, eares and heareth not, a noſe and ſmelleth not, feete and walke not: ſo to ſee a man whoſe wit is pregnant, and bodye ſtrong, to be vnexerciſed both in minde and bodye, is a ſin not to be ſuffered in the common wealth, or in the Church of God. For as the tree that beareth no frute is to be hewen downe and caſt into the fire: ſo the man that is vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Church of God, ſhall by the axe of Gods iudgement, be hewen downe and caſt into hell fire, though he were the higheſt cedar in Libanus.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, hee reproueth them in reſpect of the time, for the day is appointed to labour, and the night to reſt:<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.24.</note> 
               <hi>The ſunne ariſeth, the Lyons retire and couch in their dennes, then man goeth forth to his worke and to his labour:</hi> So this being the <hi>daye of ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2: Cor. 6.2. Gala. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>and the time accepted: wee ought while wee haue time to doe good.</hi> Mans life is but ſhorte: Firſt, becauſe we ſhould withdraw our loue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world: ſecondly, that we might not be weary of well doing: thirdly, that we ſhould not ſpend our life vnprofitablie: fourthly, to ſhew the loue of God, who for a daies labour giueth vs the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:15611:39"/> pennie of eternall life: fiftly, hereby we learn that God hath choſen man to eternall life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would ſuffer him to be heere but a little while: ſixtly, that we ſhould make very great haſte to enter into our reſt. As therefore man will labour earneſtly and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye that hee be not preuented with the night, ſo will the godlye alſo labour earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in their vocation in this precious, ſhort, and irreuocable time of their life, becauſe after death there is no daye, but night, no time accepted, but the daye of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, the idle are reproued for the continuance of time, <hi>all the daye:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a ſhame for a Chriſtian man to be idle in the church of God: a greater ſhame to be idle in the time of the Goſpell, but to be idle all daye is the greateſt ſhame in the worlde. If you will not come into the vineyard at the ſixt houre, come in at the ninth: if not at the ninth houre, come in at the eleuenth houre: but if you wil come neither at the firſt nor laſt houre, then ſhall you neuer receiue the reward of euerlaſting life: they that came in at the laſt houre ſhall be firſt, but they that came not in at all, were refuſed as loyterers, and condemned as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:15611:40"/> vnprofitable, or rather abhominable repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the poore, the ſin of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and of England.</note>Vnmercifulneſſe to the poore is a ſinne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that procureth the wrath of God vpon vs. For as God only giueth vs all that wee haue, and giueth it to vs freely &amp; abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beyond our deſert or deſire: ſo God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to feede the hungrye, to giue drinke to the thirſtye, to cloath the naked, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme the priſonner, and to viſite the ſicke, promiſing that what we giue to thoſe, we <hi>giue to his brethren:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.40.</note> and therefore wee are to ponder firſt, what a dignitie it is to be a brother to Chriſt; ſecondly, that all things are ours; thirdly, we are hereby made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to Chriſt; fourthly, wee that are mercifull excell the Angels; fiftlye, that this brotherhood doth excell all carnall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation.</p>
            <p>If then God being bountifull vnto vs, we are vnkinde to our brethren, we are iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned to eternall fire: firſt, becauſe of the facilitie of the petition, for what doth he aske? a peece of bread, a cup of drinke, an olde garment, or a peece of ſiluer: who will denye this to the hungrie, thirſtie, naked, or captiue brother of Chriſt? ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe of the miſery of him that asketh,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:15611:40"/> for he is poore, thirſtie, naked, or a priſonner. Thirdly, becauſe of the compaſsion of nature that ſhould bee in vs, for hee is a man, and therefore we muſt weigh who asketh, what he asketh, and of whome. He that asketh is a man, ſo art thou: he is fraile, ſo art thou: hee is miſerable, ſo art thou: what doth he aske? bread, drinke, a garment, or ſiluer, which is none of thine, for thou art but a ſteward of it: But thou being a ſinfull man doſt begge of God, and thou beggeſt righteouſneſſe. Now if thou being a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doſt deny thy equal, when he asketh that which is not thine: how dareſt thou being far inferiour to God, aske of him righteouſneſſe or mercie? thou wilt not giue to thy neighbour temporall things, how ſhall God giue to thee eternall things?</p>
            <p>The fourth thing that ſhould moue vs to mercie, is the deſire of the promiſe: for God promiſeth vs a kingdome:<note place="margin">Mat. 25.24. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit yee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you before the foundations of the worlde: for J was hungrie, and yee gaue me meate, I thirſted, and yee gaue me drinke, I was naked and yee clothed mee, J was a ſtranger, and yee lodged me, I was ſicke, and yee viſited mee, I was in priſon, and yee redeemed me</hi> The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God (which in dignitie is higheſt,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:15611:41"/> in libertie free, in peace ſecure, in honor glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, in cleanneſſe pure, in ſocietye of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ioyous, and perpetuall in the affluence of riches) the influence of pleaſures, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of all Saints, is promiſed for a peece of meate, a draught of drinke, a nights lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, an old garment, or a peece of ſiluer. Is not hee a wiſe marchant, that changeth lead for golde, a copiehold for an inheritance, and for a houſe a kingdome? ſo doe all thoſe that be mercifull to the poore.</p>
            <p>The fift thing that ſhould moue vs to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſſe, is the dignitie of the receiuer: for whatſoeuer ye giue to the poore, yee giue to Chriſt. We ought to giue to the poore for his owne ſake, for our ſake, and for Chriſtes ſake: for his owne ſake, becauſe if he be in the ſtate of grace, hee is the childe of God, if hee be a ſinner, he is the workemanſhip of God: and therefore albeit he is to be puniſhed, becauſe he is an offendor; yet he is to be pittied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is a man, and hee muſt ſee in vs the worke of mercifulneſſe, that hee may glorifie our Father which is in heauen. For thy owne ſake alſo thou muſt be mercifull: For <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.7. Iam. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>and there ſhall be iudgement mercileſſe to him that ſheweth no mercie:</hi> but if thou wilt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:15611:41"/> not doe it for his ſake, nor for thine owne ſake, at leaſt wiſe doe it for Chriſtes ſake, who ſaith: <hi>In as much as yee haue done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.40</note> 
               <hi>yee haue done it vnto me:</hi> for Chriſt reckoneth it giuen to himſelfe, whatſoeuer is giuen to the poore. What a dignitie then is this for vs, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede are but duſt, earth and aſhes, to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted giuers vnto him, which is the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of all things?</p>
            <p>The ſixt thing that ſhould moue vs to mercie, is the ſuper abundance of honor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt dooth vouchſafe to receaue meate, drinke, and lodging at our handes. If the Queene of England ſhould acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her ſelfe to haue receiued at our handes, meate, drinke, raiment, or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, were we not greatlye honoured? how much more when the ſonne of God, King of kinges, Lord of lords, and God of gods: doth ſo magnifie vs, that hee acknowledgeth himſelf to be indetted vnto vs, when we doe but our dutie?</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth thing that ſhould moue vs to mercye, is the iuſtice of the gift, for his owne thinges hee accepteth at our handes, as though we had giuen them: hee giueth vs bread, and yet hee ſaith, we giue him bread;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:15611:42"/> hee feedeth vs, and yet hee ſaith, we feede him; hee giueth vs wine, and yet hee ſaith, wee giue him drinke; hee giueth vs hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and yet hee ſaith wee lodge him; hee cloatheth vs, and yet hee ſaith wee cloath him; hee healeth vs when we are ſicke, and yet he ſaith, we viſite him; hee deliuereth vs being priſoners, and yet hee ſaith, we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed him. Thus the Lord of all things ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe a ſeruant, the owner of all the beaſtes of the forreſt maketh himſelfe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie,<note place="margin">Agge. 28.</note> and he that ſaith: <hi>Gold and ſiluer is mine,</hi> maketh himſelfe a beggar to prouoke vs to mercifulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe neither the facilitie of the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor the miſerie of the afflicted, nor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsion of nature, nor the deſire of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, nor the dignitie of the receiuer, nor the ſuperabundance of honor which hee giueth, nor the iuſtice of the gift can moue vs to be pittiful to the poore, therefore it is the ſin of Sodom which was burned, &amp; the ſin of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem which was ſacked, and the ſin of this iron age, which ſhall be condemned.</p>
            <p>Vnder the name of the poore, are meant the miniſters of God, poore ſcholers which are the ſeede plot of the Church, poore ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, poore impotent men, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:15611:42"/> ſicke men, priſoners and baniſhed men: to be vnmerciful to theſe is the ſinne of Sodom, and a ſinne that neuer leaueth crying to God, till it hath brought downe on the mercileſſe extreame damnation: For wee ſhould loue them, and we hate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; we ſhould heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and we ſtop our eares; we ſhould viſit them gladly, and wee diſdaine them: wee ſhould ſpeak to them gently, and we ſpeake rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; we ſhould haue compaſsion on them, and we are incompaſsionate towardes them: we ſhould do them good, and we do them harm: we ſhould defend them from euill, and wee ſmite them. Are we mercifull to the poore miniſters in theſe daies? do we giue, or rather pull away from them? what mercy is ſhewed to poore ſcholers in Oxford or Cambridge? what releefe haue ſouldiers? who refreſheth the bowels of hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger-ſtarued <hi>Lazarus?</hi> where theſe are ſpoiled or deſpiſed, there God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is ſpoyled and contemned.</p>
            <p>If theſe ſhall be condemned that will not giue their owne, what ſhal thoſe be that take away from the poore? what ſhall become of our Martiniſtes, <hi>that abhorre Idlenes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom, 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſacriledge?</hi> what ſhall become of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of England, which <hi>ioyne houſe to houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>and land to land, that there may be no dwelling
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:15611:43"/> for the poore?</hi> as wee ſee in manye deſolate places of england. What ſhall befall them which <hi>grinde the faces of the poore, and bray them as it were in a morter? what vengeance ſhal they receiue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 3.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>which hate the good and loue the euill, and plucke off their skins from them, and their fleſh from their bones, and they eate alſo the fleſh of my people</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and flay off their skinne from them, and they breake their bones, and chop them in peeces as for the potte, and as fleſh within the cauldron. Martin</hi> findeth fault that a Miniſter ſhould haue two benefices, but for a nobleman or Gentleman which hath ſixe hee reprehendeth it not. The Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (ſaith he) ioine houſe to houſe; there be thoſe in England that haue &amp; doe dayly pull downe houſes, wherein haue beene families like flocks of ſheepe, &amp; now there is nothing but a ſhepheard and his dogge: for the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful land is become a wilderneſſe. What is the reaſon, he reproueth the miniſters ſo ſharply, and leaueth the other vnreproued? <hi>rete non tenditur accipitri nec miluo, his qui malefaciunt nobis: illis qui nihil faciunt, tenditur:</hi> the net is not laid for the hawke or the kite, or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do ill; it is laid for them that do no harme. So no man ſpeaketh againſt him that commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſacriledge, Vſurie, violence and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:15611:43"/> which <hi>burne vp the vineyard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 3.14. Abac. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>and haue the ſpoile of the poore in their houſes;</hi> and <hi>build vp Sion with bloud: as a cage is full of birdes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.27.</note> 
               <hi>ſo are their houſes full of riches gotten by deceit, thereby they are become great and rich.</hi> Vnmercifulneſſe is the ſinne of Sodome, much more is rapine, and ſacriledge, violence and vſurie. All theſe are in England, therefore perpetuall deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is at hand. Will ye ſee the guilt of ſinne? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Cain</hi> wandering. Will yee ſee the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſinne? remember <hi>Saul</hi> raging. Will yee ſee the feare of ſin? remember <hi>Baltaſar</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Will yee ſee the ignominie of ſinne? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Haman</hi> hanging. Wil yee ſee the end of ſinne? remember Sodom and Gomorrha; and the countries round about burning in the vengeance of eternall fire for euer.</p>
            <p>The ſinnes of Sodome were not onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and many, but alſo exceeding great,<note place="margin">The ſinnes of Sodome are exceeding great, and ſo are the ſinnes of England.</note> and ſo are the ſinnes of England. Sin is aggrauated 1. by the multitude of ſinners: 2. by euil exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Magiſtrates, miniſters, and fathers: 3. by impunitie: 4. by encouragement in euill: 5. by ſtudie to do miſchiefe: 6. by perſeuerance in ſinnes. In Sodome there was multitude of offenders, for they did offend all; of euerye age, as children, young and old men, of euery
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:15611:44"/> ſexe, as men and women; &amp; of euerie eſtate; as the magiſtrate and ſubiect, the prieſt and people, the maiſter and ſeruant, the father &amp; ſonne, and the husband and wife.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Children haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>es. Pſal. 22.31.</note>Firſt, for our children (I tremble to ſpeake it) being our <hi>ſeede that ſhould ſerue the Lord after vs:</hi> as ſoone as they are borne they are ſo accuſtomed to blaſpheme, that they fill euerie ſtreete, euerye houſe, and euery high way with it: and if it be true which the wiſe man ſaith: that the plague of God departeth not from the houſe of the ſwearer: then no doubt it will fall vpon the poſteritie of our Engliſh nation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1. Yong men haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes.</note>Secondly, for yong men which <hi>ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Lord in the daies of their youth,</hi> their heads are full of drunkenneſſe, their eyes full of adulterie, their toungful of filthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, their eares full of ribald<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, their handes full of bloud, their feete runne to vanitie, their vnderſtanding is blinde, their affection froward, their heart is lewde and vnſearcheable. If they learne not this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon out of the Pſalme.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7.</note> 
               <hi>O remember not the ſinnes of our youth, but according to thy mercie thinke vppin vs:</hi> they muſt learne this leſſon to their confuſion,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>deſtruction and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:15611:44"/> is in our waies, there is no feare of God before our eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning olde men,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.2. Olde men haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes.</note> they ſhould be <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, graue, modeſt, ſound in faith, charitie and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi> They ſhould be ſober, and they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to drunkenneſſe; chaſte, and they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to wantonneſſe; diſcreete, and they are moſt fooliſh; ſound in faith, and they are as ignorant as horſe and mule; in charitie, and they are full of enuie; in patience, and they are moſt waiward.</p>
            <p>You haue heard of euery age, now ſhall you heare of euery ſexe, that is of men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It hath bene an ancient ſtrife whether is the moſt excellent creature,<note place="margin">Men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue exceeding great ſinnes.</note> the man or the woman; but now they ſtriue whether may excel other in vitiouſneſſe. For men are recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Papiſts, ſo are women; men are murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, ſo are women, for they murder their own infants, men are adulterers, theeues, ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and couetous perſons, ſo are women. In <hi>S. Peters</hi> time <hi>wiues vvere ſo ſubiect to their husbands, that they which obeyed not the word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>might without the word be won by the conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their wiues, whileſt they behelde their pure conuerſation, which was in feare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.5.</note> In <hi>Paules</hi> time <hi>Lois and Eunice brought vp</hi> Timothie <hi>in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:15611:45"/> word of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 8.23.</note> In Chriſtes time <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene out of whome went ſeauen diuels, and Ioanna the wife of Chuza Herods ſteward. Suſanna and many others miniſtred vnto Chriſt of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> Though <hi>Nabal</hi> was a churle, yet <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail</hi> his wife was a vertuous woman. But in our daies it is as it was in Sodome; children yong men and olde, yea men and women, all do ſin, they ſin often, and they ſin greeuouſlye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Magiſtrates haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes. Iath. 18.21. Jer. 4.22.</note> Now let vs looke into all eſtates; magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhould <hi>be wiſe, feare God, loue the truth, and abhorre couetouſneſſe.</hi> But our magiſtrates are <hi>wiſe to doe euill, to doe well they haue no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> They ſhould feare God, and they feare man; they ſhould deale vprightlye, and they turne iuſtice into oppreſsion; they ſhould ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre couetouſneſſe, and they ioyne houſe to houſe, &amp; land to land, &amp; they eate vp the poor like bread. The foundation then of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth being feble, the walles of our vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard being tottering, and the hedges of our Church being broken downe; what is to be looked for but a ſpeedie &amp; fearful deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Magiſtrates are called Gods, to ſhew that they ſhould be meek,<note place="margin">Num. 12.3. 1. King 4.34. Heb. 1.2.</note> wiſe, iuſt. They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods for the aduancement of their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for as <hi>Iacob</hi> called <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſonne after his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:15611:45"/> owne name, ſo God to honor magiſtrates cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them after his own name; becauſe neither the loftineſſe of their eſtate, nor the pleaſures of this life, nor the tempeſtes nor troubles of this dangerous worlde, nor the flatteries of the wicked ſhould make them to peruert iuſtice: but Gods law ſhould be their law, Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhould be their honour, Gods kingdome ſhould be their kingdome, and Gods enemies ſhould be their enemies. And therefore the wicked may not be ſpared either for loue of friend, hatred of enemie, deſire of reward, or feare of ſuperiour. To be called Gods ſeruant is an honorable title, to be called diſciple of Chriſt is more honorable, and to be called the ſonne of God moſt honorable; but to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led God, this is a name, then the which there cannot be a greater. Men may be called noble of their parents, and learned of their artes: but to be called Gods is a nobilitie that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of vertue: therfore for a God to be a briber, ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, ſwearer, lyer, drunkard, or vſurer, is a moſt abſurd thing. <hi>Should ſuch a man as J flee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 6.11.</note> ſaith <hi>(Nehemiah)</hi> the Prophet: So, for a magiſtrate to be a couetous God, an idoll God, or a bellie God, is a great ſhame. For as <hi>Dauid</hi> excelling <hi>Saul</hi> in vertue, was choſen to be king, and <hi>Saul</hi> reiected, ſo the wicked ſhalbe humbled, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:15611:46"/> the vertuous exalted. Now becauſe our high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers haue in them baſe villanies, our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are tirants, our heads are giddy, our men are beaſts, and our Gods diuels: it is a fearfull token of our future deſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Subiects haue exceeding great ſinnes.</note> As the Magiſtrates haue ſinnes exceeding great, ſo haue the priuate men. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> willeth vs to ſubmit our ſelues to our magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates; which ſubiection containeth 5. things: firſte, that wee acknowledge them to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed our gouernours from God, for hee himſelfe ſaith,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>by me kings doe raigne:</hi> Secondly, that wee ſhould yeelde them reuerence with feare: 3. that we ſhould obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of heart: 4. that we be thankfull vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heart &amp; deed: 5. that of all the Princes acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we giue a gentle interpretation. For as a bitter medicine doth oftentimes more good then a ſweete: ſo the actions of Princes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they like or diſlike vs, ought to be gently interpreted. But wee thinke not our gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to be aduaunced by God; for if we did, then ſhould wee reuerence them; but wee <hi>as beaſtes voide of reaſon, ſpeake euill of them that are in authoritie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 10.</note> And for reuerence we render contempt, for obedience, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; for thankefulneſſe, ingratitude: and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:15611:46"/> like buſie bodies, we giue a ſiniſter interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of all publike actions. Euen as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple murmured againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo doe we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her maieſtie: and the reaſon is, euery man is wiſe in his owne conceites, euery man will bee a head, euery one a teacher, euery one a reformer; no man wil be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, a learner, or a Diſciple. Heereof the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> prophecied long before:<note place="margin">Eſay 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall preſume againſt the ancient, and the wiſe againſt the honourable.</hi> If this ſaying were true in the Prophets time, it is moſt true in our time. This was the wracke of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and this will be the ruine of England. For our young diuines being children in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding (making themſelues to be Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the lawe, and yet vnderſtanding not what they ſpeak, or whereof they affirme) do ſpeak againſt the fathers of the Church, not onely with permiſsion, but with approbation and applauſe. And if they ſhal be thus dealt withall that are <hi>worthie of double honour;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.15.</note> then others may think alſo,<note place="margin">Miniſters haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes.</note> that their honours will fall to the duſt.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Miniſters of our lande, which ſhould be <hi>the light of the world and the fault of the earth;</hi> how darke,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.14.</note> and vnſauerye
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:15611:47"/> are they?<note place="margin">Zach. 11.17. Ioh. 10.5. Ioh. 10.8. Ioh. 10.12.</note> for ſome are <hi>idols,</hi> ſome are <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> ſome are <hi>theeues and robbers,</hi> ſome are <hi>hirelinges.</hi> The idol ſhepheard is an abhomination, the ſtranger they know not, the theefe and robber doth kill and deſtroye, the hireling doth flie when he ſeeth the wolfe comming. <hi>There be many falſe Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.22.</note> 
               <hi>and falſe Chriſtes, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders to deceiue the very elect, if it were poſsible.</hi> Yea as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All ſeek their owne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>and not thoſe thinges which are Jeſus Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which of our Biſhops or Cleargie, doth exhibit to the maintenance of poor ſchollers in Oxford or Cambridge, being the ſeminary of the Church of God? I know many fine wits and yong men of good hope, who for want of exhibition, muſt either applye themſelues to be ſeruing men, which is not well; or elſe goe to Rhemes which is worſe; or elſe to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abaptiſticall Schiſmatiques, to trouble the peace of the Church, which is worſt of al. The noble and wealthie of this land ſhalbe iuſtly condemned, for that they haue not bene bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to the profeſſors of learning; but moſt iuſtly we of the ſpiritualtie; for hauing beene nouriſhed our ſelues by this godly meanes, yet we neglect the doing of ſo honorable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:15611:47"/> an action. Albeit therefore many haue great liuings, yet as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.14.</note> they haue it <hi>but to liue:</hi> 
               <q>to liue ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> not to be rich, not to be proud, not to be wanton, not that hee ſhould build great pallaces, not that he ſhould aduance his kinred with the wealth of the Church, nor marry his Nephewes, his Sonnes and his Daughters with the Church goods.</q> Two thinges I note out of this ſaying of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> the one that Biſhops had Sonnes and daughters, and therfore were married, againſt the Papiſts; the other is, they had great welth, againſt the Martiniſtes: to vſe theſe thinges is lawfull, to abuſe them is vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>Finally, ſome of our Miniſters are as coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous as <hi>Ahab,</hi> ſome as full of ſcoffing, as <hi>Jſmael,</hi> ſome as wanton as <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſome as traiterous as <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſome as ignorant as an aſſe, and ſome as ambitious as the diuel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaide.<note place="margin">Chriſoſtom.</note> If thou ſeeſt a tree that beareth no fruite, the cauſe is in the root; <q>ſo where the people liue wickedly, the cauſe is in the Miniſters. For either they are ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant they cannot, or ſo fearefull they dare not, or ſo ſlouthfull they will not doe their dutye.</q> And therfore he ſaith, many in name, and few in deede; and in his eight Homily vpon the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:15611:48"/> third of the Actes, hee maruelleth that any of vs do enter into the kingdome of heauen: for as the parrets ſpake the wordes of men, ſo we ſpeake the wordes of the Apoſtles; and not only our wordes are vaine, but our workes are abhominable.</p>
            <p>Concerning the hearers of the worde, from ſome the Diuell ſtealeth the word out of their hearts,<note place="margin">Hearers haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes.</note> others are choaked with the cares and pleaſures of this life, others are ſo hard hearted and impenitent, that a man were as good preach to the incenſible ſtones, as to them. We are commaunded not only to heare the word, but to vnderſtand it; <hi>Heare and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,</hi> ſaith Chriſt;<note place="margin">Mat. 15.10.</note> neither ſhould we only vnderſtand it, but laye it vp in our heart; and therefore <hi>Mary</hi> is commended,<note place="margin">Luke. 10.51.</note> that ſhe <hi>kepe all Chriſtes ſayings in her heart.</hi> And we ſhould not onely loue the word,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> but be <hi>doers of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome will neuer heare, as our Papiſtes; ſome doe heare and not vnderſtand, as the ignorant; ſome vnderſtand the word, but loue it not, as the hypocrite; ſome doe heare, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and loue it, but are not doers of the word, as vaine Goſpellers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:15611:48"/> and out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, exhorte vvith all long ſuffering and doctrine; for the time vvill come, when they will not ſuffer wholeſome doctrine, but hauing their eares itching, ſhall after their owne luſtes get them a heape of teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learned Diuines haue noted eight cauſes of hereſies: the firſt is ignorance, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede is the mother of ſeductions. For igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is not onely deſtitute of vpright iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo is in danger of the wickedneſſe of deceitfull men, and therefore the Apoſtle commandeth, <hi>Brethren be not children in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>but as concerning maliciouſneſſe be children.</hi> The craftie Papiſts therefore which got both gaine and Lordſhip ouer the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, did care by all meanes to keepe the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued multitude in ignorance. Secondly, a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering mind followeth this ignorance; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it commeth to paſſe, that they which are children in vnderſtanding, are carried about with euery blaſt of vaine doctrine. This wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the Apoſtle reproueth,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Hee gaue ſome to be Apoſtles and ſome Prophets, ſome Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and ſome Paſtors and teachers, for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering togither of the Saintes, for the worke of the miniſtery, and for the glorification of the bodie of Chriſt, till we all meet togither in the vnitie of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:15611:49"/> faith, and knowledge of the ſame God, vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt. That we henceforth be no more children, wauering, and carried away with euerie winde of doctrine by the deceit of men, and with craftineſſe, whereby they lye in waite to deceiue.</hi> This ignorance therefore and wauering of minde, doth open the doore to all hereſies and errors, and maketh the vnskilfull multitude to follow heretiques &amp; deceitfull men. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where the vice of curioſitie taketh effect, there euery hereticall deceit preuaileth: for aſſoone as any new or vnaccuſtomed thing is taught, they which are curious, deſiring to know what it is, doe greedily heare, read, and entertaine it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this happeneth to them which are as it were ſlaues to their luſtes, when they heare a doctrine pleaſing their deſires, by and by they note it, and apply both their eares and their heart to it. Of this the Apoſtle foretold; <hi>For the time will come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>when they will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vvholeſome doctrine, but hauing their eares itching, ſhall after their owne luſtes get them an heape of teachers, and ſhall turne their eares from the truth, and ſhall be giuen vnto fables.</hi> Sound doctrine to the corrupt fleſhe languiſhing in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:15611:49"/> deſires, is as a medicine to a ſick man: for euen as a faithfull Phiſitian is greeuous to a ſicke man, forbidding him thoſe thinges which he greatly deſireth, and commanding him thoſe things which are contrary to his deſires; and as a deceiuer is acceptable, who regarding his own profit, yeeldeth to his deſires: in like maner the Apoſtle did foreſee that the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of truth would be greeuous to carnall men, and ſeruants of their own luſts; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would turn away their eares from it to falſe teachers, &amp; their fables (being not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous but ioyous to the fleſh) they ſhuld gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily embrace. 5. Whoſoeuer hath ſuch itching eares, they are alwaies vnſtable. 6 S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith; that <hi>vnlearned and vnſtable men peruert the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vnto their owne deſtruction:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.16.</note> for they are lighter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a reed &amp; moued with euery wind. 7 Ignorance therfore ioyned with a deſire of noueltie, being coupled with inſtabilitie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſimple people to receiue chaffe for wheate, droſſe for gold, vineger for wine, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for meat, &amp; falſhood for truth. Some hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are compared to ſtones, they profite no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; ſome to thornes, they choake the ſeede which is in them with voluptuouſneſſe; ſome to Swine, for they raile againſt the Preachers:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:15611:50"/> ſome to dogs, for they are willing to deuour vs. This froward and crooked generation that deſpiſe the word and kil the prophets that are ſent to them, ſhal haue their houſe deſolate.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fathers haue exceeding great ſinnes.</note>Fathers alſo haue exceeding great ſins. For fathers owe to their ſons. 1. loue; 2 dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; 3. wiſe gouernement; that they be not corrupted either with too much cockering, or with ouermuch auſterity; 4. to bring vp their children in good arts &amp; godlines; 5. to correct them if they do not their duty. But our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in ſteed of loue vſe fond affection: and for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment we may ſay as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaide, I rule Athens, my wife ruleth me, and my child ruleth my wife: and wheras they ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in good artes and in pittie, they are inſtructed in carding, dicing, dancing, haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and hunting. Laſtlye, where they ſhould correct their children for offending, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in their wickednes. <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> did curſe their father that did beget the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the mother that did beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they were borne to ſuch trouble and miſeries: but the children of our time wil curſe their parentes becauſe they are nouriſhed vp in wickedneſſe for the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of hell, which are ceaſeles, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, &amp; remediles. Fathers wil teach their ſons
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:15611:50"/> to haue their barns full of corne with the <hi>rich man,</hi> their purſes full of mony with the rich glutton, their houſes ful of plate with <hi>Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> their backes full of gorgeous apparrel with <hi>Herode,</hi> their table full of daintye diſhes with <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> but they are vnfurniſhed of all kind of vertues and heauenly graces: and therefore though they &amp; their parents ſpend their daies in wealthines, yet in a moment they go down to hell.</p>
            <p>Children owe to their parents,<note place="margin">Children haue excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great ſinnes.</note> firſt the loue of the heart, and they wiſh them dead to haue their goods; ſecondly honor, and they diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their parents; thirdly ſuſtentation in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie, and they rob their parents; fourthly ſeruice in all obſequies, &amp; they are rebellious; fiftly reuerence in words, and they are taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: ſixtly obedience in honeſt things, and they are diſobedient; ſeuenthly pardon in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and they like <hi>Cham</hi> diſcouer their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhame; eightly tolerance in aduerſitye, and they refuſe to acknowledge their parents; Therfore noble houſes are decaied, the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the rich are brought to ſcarſitie, the extorcioner conſumeth their wealth, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible is the end of the vnrighteous generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For either with <hi>Abſolom</hi> they are hanged,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:15611:51"/> or with the Sonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> they are ſlaine; or with the ſonnes of <hi>Iob</hi> their braines are daſht out; or with the ſonnes of <hi>Saul</hi> they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed; or with the children of Ieruſalem they are brought to a perpetuall deſolation. To tel here how ſome are ſcoffers with <hi>Iſmael;</hi> ſome adulterers with the ſons of <hi>Eli;</hi> ſome bribers as the ſonnes of <hi>Samuel;</hi> ſome theeues as the ſonnes of <hi>Achan;</hi> ſome gluttons as the ſonnes of <hi>Iob;</hi> ſome Atheiſts, neither ſeruing God, nor honoring the Magiſtrate, nor louing the Miniſter, nor reuerencing the aged, nor obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their father, nor ſubmitting themſelues to their mother, nor pittying the poore, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their conſanguinitie, were too long for me to ſpeak, and tedious for you to heare: only this I ſay, our children are the children of wrath and of endles deſtruction for the moſt part.</p>
            <p>Euil example of Magiſtrats, Miniſters and Fathers,<note place="margin">Euil example of Magiſtrats maketh ſin exceeding great.</note> are an other meanes to aggrauate ſin. For when <hi>Iſrael</hi> coupled himſelf to <hi>Baal Peor,</hi> the Lord being angrye ſaide thus to <hi>Moſes.</hi> Num. 25.4. <hi>Take all the heads of the people and hang them vp before the Lord againſt the ſun, that the indignation of the Lordes wrath may ceaſe from Jſrael.</hi> Magiſtrates ſhould be men no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:15611:51"/> in birth, in knowledge and in vertues. As they haue a crown of pure gold, ſo muſt they ſhine in puritie to their ſubiectes; as they are deckt with precious ſtons, ſo muſt they ſhine in excellent vertues; as they weare chaines of gold, ſo they muſt be endued with wiſdome, iuſtice, fortitude and temperance; as they haue a ſcepter, ſo they may not he be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from iuſtice to oppreſsion, or from clemencye to fooliſh pittie. They are the Sun of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, therefore if they be darkened, there muſt needes followe horror and confuſion: they are the heart of the political bodie, if they be poyſoned with the venome of ſinne, the whole body muſt needs be infected to death. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> made all the people to commit ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; <hi>Baaſha ſlew Jeroboam and al his houſe, and left none aliue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. king. 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the ſinnes of Jeroboam which be committed, and wherewith he made Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to ſin by prouocation.</hi> So is it written of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſha,</hi> that he made all Iſrael to ſin.<note place="margin">1. King. 16.11.</note> But <hi>Baaſha</hi> and all his poſteritie were deſtroyed for it. <hi>Zimri</hi> alſo was burnt,<note place="margin">1. King. 16.18.19.</note> becauſe hee walked in the ſinnes of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and made all Iſrael to ſin. <hi>Omri</hi> alſo walked in the ſins of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 16.26.</note> and made al Iſrael to ſin. The like may be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Ahab</hi> and of other wicked Kings: for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15611:52"/> there are many cauſes why they fal: 1. the lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines of their eſtate, becauſe they haue none to controll them; 2. the abundance of al things; 3. the delights which they haue in this world; 4. their libertie becauſe they are aboue al, and ſubiect to none; 5. the example of wicked go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors; 6. the troubles of worldly thinges; 7. ſlatterye, then the which nothing is more pernicious.<note place="margin">Euil exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters maketh ſin exceeding great.</note> The euill example of Miniſters doth likewiſe make ſin heinous, for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter muſt be an example to his flock, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of good workes: but if hee be either a proud perſon and louer of preheminence, as <hi>Diotrophes</hi> was; or a louer of the world, as <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> was; or a couetous caitiffe as <hi>Iudas</hi> was; or a falſe Prophet, as were thoſe that fed at the table of <hi>Iezabel;</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (no doubt) but they draw the people from religion to ſuperſtition, from the ſpirit to the fleſh, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt to the world, and from God to the diuell. If there be a tree withered (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) the fault is in the roote:<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> ſo if ye ſee the people irreligious, the fault is in the Miniſters, and this is a true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Auguſtine, Gregory</hi> and <hi>Bernard;</hi> He that liueth ill in the ſight of thoſe ouer whome he ruleth, as much as in him lyeth killeth them; for whoſe life is abhominable, his doctrine ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:15611:52"/> not be acceptable.</p>
            <p>There are three thinges neceſſarye for a Preacher,<note place="margin">3. Things neceſſarie for a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> knowledge which is noted in the booke ſent to <hi>Ezechiel;</hi> eloquence which is noted in the hot cole that purged <hi>Eſay;</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of life, which is noted in the hand ſent to <hi>Ieremy.</hi> If a Preacher lacke knowledge, hee is an idol; if hee lacke vtterance, hee is an infant; but if he lacke holines of life, hee is a diuel. It ſorroweth me to thinke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of England, for either we neuer learne to ſpeake, which is ſlothfulneſſe; or elſe we ſpeak before we learne, which is raſhenes; or elſe we learn &amp; neuer ſpeak, which is idlenes; or els we ſpeak to pleaſe itching eares, which is flattery; or elſe we ſpeak falſely againſt the truth, which is impietie.</p>
            <p>The euil example therefore of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters which haue gifts giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them from aboue, to gather togither the body of Chriſt, and yet do ſcatter: which ſhould build vp the houſe of the Lord, and do deſtroy it, which ſhould ſow the pure ſeede of the word of vnitie, and they ſow the darnel of diſſention, is an other heinous crime which prouoketh to eternall deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of Fathers, who parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:15611:53"/> the name of God our eternal father,<note place="margin">Euil example of Father maketh ſin exceeding great.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhould beget vs in the worde of truth bring vs vp in the feare of the Lord, and by their example teach vs to worſhippe our God, and ſerue him in holines &amp; righteouſnes all the dayes of our life. But (good Lord) how far are we from this dutye? for we bring them vp in dancing, dicing, and daliance, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; we teach them to oppreſſe &amp; deceiue in bargaining, we confirme them in idolatrye and ſchiſmes, and make them inſtruments of iniquitie. What is the reaſon that we haue ſo many recuſant Papiſts in England but onely this, the ill example of their fathers? What is the reaſon our Saboths be openly prophaned throughout this land? ill example of the fathers: for whereas they ſhuld ſpecially care that day of the Lord, to enſtruct their families in the faith of Chriſt, they do that daye bring them forth to leade their dance in contempt both of Gods commandement and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Happie are thoſe that may ſay with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 22 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Our fathers hoped in thee, they truſted in thee, they hoped in thee, and were not aſhamed; they tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in thee &amp; were not confounded.</hi> But we muſt pray with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Remember not our old ſinnes, but haue mercy vpon vs and that ſoone, for we are
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:15611:53"/> come to great miſerie.</hi> For if God be not merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs, we ſhall all both the father and children come ſhortly and ſodenly to eternall miſerie.</p>
            <p>Impunitie alſo cauſeth our ſinnes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great.<note place="margin">Impunitie maketh ſins exceeding great. Eccle. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſeene all thinges</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>in the daies of my vanity, there is a iuſt man that periſheth in his iuſtice, &amp; there is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man that continueth long in his malice:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 21.23.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaking of theſe ſaith; <hi>They ſpende all their daies in welthineſſe, &amp; in a moment they goe downe to hell. Dauid</hi> ſaith thus,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33, 12.</note> 
               <hi>And theſe are the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, yet proſper they alwaies, and encreaſe in riches.</hi> And a little after he ſaith; <hi>Surely thou haſt ſet them in ſlipperie places, O how ſodenly do they pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, conſume, &amp; come to a fearfull end? Auguſtine</hi> in his ſelect ſentences thus writeth,<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> the fortie two ſentence. <q>There is nothing more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the felicity of ſinners, whereby a penal impunitie is nouriſhed, and the euill will as an inward enemy is ſtrengthened.<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> on the firſt chapter of the Hebrues &amp; his ſecond Homily thus ſaith; <hi>But beſides all other euils, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue alſo this miſchief, that rich men ſinning wickedly, are defended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſhments:</hi> &amp; he that poſſeſſeth riches though he alwaies ſin yet he is not reſtrained with any puniſhment, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:15611:54"/> he receiueth the wounds of ſins with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any remedies, and no man checketh him for it. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in a treatiſe hee hath of the Martyrs ſaith; The men of this world are vnhappily happy, for they are for a time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, and for euer miſerable: but the Martyres are happily miſerable, for they are miſerable for a ſeaſon, and happie for euer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For that then the manifeſt and many ſinnes of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d are not puniſhed, we haue no cauſe to reioyce in it, but rather to feare that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of our puniſhment will be more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, for though he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth with leaden heels, hee ſtriketh with yron handes, recompenſing the tarditie therof with the grauity. Being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſee the idolaters to ſin manifeſtly, the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers to ſweare outragiouſly, the Saboths of the Lord to be prophaned notoriouſly, murthers to be pardoned, adulterers to be winckt at, robberies to be counted purchace, ſlanderings &amp; railings to be accounted zeale, and couetouſnes to be reckoned theft, &amp; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion wiſdom: ſith I ſay, al theſe ſinnes are not only vnpuniſhed which is lamentable: but alſo maintained, which is damnable: it cannot be, but that God which made all the world of nothing, will bring the wicked to nothing: &amp;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:15611:54"/> he that gouerneth in equitie, wil deſtroy them that worke iniquitie. He is by name almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, therfore he ſhal conſume away al the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked like droſſe. He is the Lord of hoſtes, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, Angels, and deuils are at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; he is the holy God of heauen, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will deſtroy all the wicked from the earth: he is a king for euer, therefore all the wicked kingdom of the earth ſhalbe brought to deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as the Preacher ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccle. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not ſpeedely exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, therefore the heart of the children of men is fully ſet in them to doe euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Pontius</hi> in his 9, chapter of liberalitie,<note place="margin">An example for Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wiues, Pontius.</note> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; that a certain rich woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, had but one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſonne, whom ſhe brought vp ſo wantonly, that he became a theefe, and was brought to the gallowes: and ſeeing his mother, hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſpeake ſecretlye with her, and when ſhe put forth her mouth to kiſſe him, hee Bit of her noſthrilles and did ſpitte them on the ground (vſing theſe wordes) let this be an example for motherly education.</q> 
               <hi>Senica</hi> the maiſter of <hi>Nero,</hi> which is ſaide to be a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his vices, not becauſe hee did prouoke him to euils, but becauſe hee did not reſtraine him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, he is reported to be butcherly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of <hi>Nero</hi> his ſcholler. <hi>Hemingius</hi> on the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:15611:55"/> ſecond epiſtle of <hi>Iohn,</hi> noteth that a fellow was accuſed of 7. murders. The iudge being great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mooued with the atrocitie of ſo heinous crimes, ſtudied what worthie puniſhment might be inflicted on him. An Aduocat plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the tranſgreſſor, proued that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor had committed but one murther and the Iudge the other ſix: and being demanded how, he replied, that if the homicide had bene put to death at the firſt murder as hee deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, then thoſe ſix had not bene ſlaine. The pardon therefore of the iudge, was the cauſe that thoſe other ſix were ſlaine. To this may be added the fearefull break-neck of <hi>Eli,</hi> who for not puniſhing his ſons, drew a tragical pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment vpon both himſelfe and his ſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Let euerye Prince therefore draw out his ſword, and euery father exerciſe his rod, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſcourge of Gods wrath, &amp; the ſword of vengeance will ſodenly and ſeuerely fal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them;<note place="margin">Pro. 13.24. Syr 7.6. Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſin, maketh ſin exceeding great. Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>for he that ſpareth the rod hateth the childe. Seeke not to be a iudge, leaſt thou be not able to take away iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Encouragement in ſin, is another thing that maketh ſin exceeding great: do not our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers and theeues, encourage one another to miſchiefe, ſaying: <hi>Come with vs, we will lay wait
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:15611:55"/> for bloud, and lye priuilie for the innocent without a cauſe, we will ſwallow them vp aliue like a graue euen whole, as thoſe that goe downe into the pit: We ſhall finde all precious riches, and fill our houſes with ſpoile. Caſt in thy lot among vs, we will all haue one purſe.</hi> Doe not our harlots encourage men in wickedneſſe, ſaying as doth the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot.<note place="margin">Pro. 17.18. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Come let vs take our fill with loue vntill the morning, let vs take our pleaſure in daliance, for mine husband is not at home, he is gone a iourney far off. He hath taken with him a bagge of ſiluer, and will come home at the time appointed: and ſtollen waters are ſweete, and the bread that is priuilye eaten hath a good taſte.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 9.17.</note> Doe not our extortioners and vſurers animate one an other in miſchiefe? ſaying:<note place="margin">Sap. 2.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs oppreſſe the poore that is righteous, let vs not ſpare the widowe, nor reuerence the white haires of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that haue liued many yeares. Let our ſtrength be the law of vnrighteouſneſſe: for the thing that is feeble is reproued as vnprofitable.</hi> Doe not our couetous cornmongers prouoke one another to afflict the people of God, as did the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in <hi>Amos</hi> time, ſaying:<note place="margin">Amos. 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>When will the new moneth begin, that we may ſell corne, and the ſabaoth that we may ſet forth wheat, and make the Ephaſmall and the ſhekel great, and falſifie the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:15611:56"/> weights by deceit: that we may buye the poore for ſiluer, and the needie for ſhooes, and ſell the refuſe of the wheate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe thinges be among the people of England, as they were among the Iewes; or rather if England doth iuſtify Ieruſalem, as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem iuſtified Sodome and Gomorrha: then no doubt as God ſpared not the naturall oliue, ſo hee will not ſpare the wilde: for we bluſhe not to commit idolatrye and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to prophane our Sabaoth, to rebell, to murder, to go a whoring, to rob, to oppreſſe, to commit vſurie, to ſlaunder our brethren, or reuile our fathers. Very well ſaith <hi>Tullie:</hi> without ſhamefaſtneſſe nothing is right, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is honeſt. But better ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſhamefaſtneſſe is the glory of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, the keeper of a good name, the honor of life, the ſeat of vertues, the praiſe of nature, and the badge of all honeſtie: but where this vertue wanteth, there is ſcorne and contempt of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Studie io doe miſchiefe maketh ſins exceeding great. Mich. 2.1.</note>Study to do miſchiefe is alſo another thing that maketh ſinne haynous. <hi>Wo vnto them that imagine iniquitie, &amp; worke wickedneſſe vpon their beds, when the morning is light they practize it, becauſe their head hath power.</hi> The ſoule of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:15611:56"/> man being made after the image of God, ought to haue God alwaies for his obiect.</p>
            <p>So ſaith <hi>Mary:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1.46.47.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirite reioyceth in God my Sauiour.</hi> For the ſoule is more excellent, then all the creatures of the world, and all things are vile in reſpect of the ſoule. Golde being in dirt is defiled, but the ſoule is not defiled with the bodie of clay: Wine mingled with water is corrupted, but the ſoule ioyned with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, is pure.</p>
            <p>The Starres and the Sunne are darkened with the cloudes, but the ſoule of man ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, though being hid in an obſcure bodie: and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> ſetteth it downe moſt plainely, where hee ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule longeth yea and fainteth for the courts of the Lord: for my heart and my fleſhe reioyce in the liuing God.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt plainelye ſaith:<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> Thou haſt made vs O Lord, for thee therefore my heart is greatly vnquiet, if it do not reſt onely in thee.</p>
            <p>O ſoule (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) made after the image of GOD, beautified with his likenes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed with Chriſtes bloud, eſpouſed to him in faith, endued with the holy ghoſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted among the Angels, capable of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; an heire of bliſſe, what haſt thou to do
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:15611:57"/> with the fleſh? The habitation of the ſoule by affection is in heauen, as proueth <hi>Paul, Our conuerſation is in heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.20.</note> It is a baſe thing therefore to take a cottage for a cittie; the worlde is a cottage, heauen is the cittie of Saintes. When then the ſoule of man deſireth golde, hee can neuer haue all the gold of the worlde: when he deſireth rule he can neuer haue the rule of all the world; when he hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for the praiſe of men, he cannot haue the praiſe of all the worlde: but that ſoule which poſſeſſeth Chriſt, poſſeſſeth all things. As God hath giuen vs Chriſt Ieſu, ſo hath <hi>he giuen vs all thinges.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> Who will then ſtudie for riches, which is vanitie; or for pleaſure, which is hurtfull; or for ſinne, which is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: and forſake God which is truth, Chriſt which is mercie, and the holy Ghoſt which is conſolation.</p>
            <p>Finally, all earthly things be of a ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, the things in heauen (which are the obiect of the ſoule) are eternall. All things in earth are greeuous, for they are full of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; things in heauen are delightful. The ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of mortall things do not performe thoſe thinges they promiſe: for as <hi>Baſil</hi> noteth: Things paſt are vaniſhed and paſt our ſenſes; thinges preſent ſlee away before they be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:15611:57"/> things to come ſith they are not preſent afflict vs with their want. All worldly things are vnſtable: for <hi>as a floure they ſprout vp, and fall againe, and neuer continue in one eſtate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 14.2.</note> for we are whole and ſicke, rich and poore. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they that gather riches, cannot tel to whom they ſhall leaue them. To ſet our delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on ſhort things and not in eternall; to ſet our ſtudies on troubleſome thinges, not in happie things; to ſet our affections on earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges that content vs not, and leaue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly things that yeeld full contentation; to apply our mind to the inſtable thinges of this worlde, leauing the certaine treaſures of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is a ſinne that argueth Gods diſpleaſure, and procureth a ſpeedie and fearefull deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Perſeuerance in ſinne is another thing,<note place="margin">Perſeuerance in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſinne exceeding great.</note> that procureth the vengeance of God to fall ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitablie vpon vs. An hundred yeares was the arke in making, and in all that time the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple repented not; therfore the flood came vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them and drowned them. <hi>Lot</hi> preached to Sodome and Gomorrha, they repented not but vexed the ſpirit of <hi>Lot;</hi> therfore fire from heauen conſumed them. To Ieruſalem did God ſend his Prophets, wiſe men and Scribes, but the people did kill and crucifie them,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:15611:58"/> ſcourge &amp; perſecute them from citie to citie, therefore their houſe is made deſolate. So to the people of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (I ſorrow to write it) the Goſpell is the <hi>ſmell of death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.6. Rom. 2.4. Gal. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>the long ſuffering of God is abuſed to impenitencie.</hi> Chriſtian <hi>libertie is turned into wantonneſſe:</hi> the ſupper of the Lord is receiued to <hi>our iudgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 11.29.</note> Chriſt himſelfe is a <hi>ſtone to ſtumble at,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and a rocke of offence.</hi> The conſcience of men is defiled,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> therefore <hi>nothing is clean to them,</hi> Wherfore this exceeding great ſinne of obſtinacie is to be puniſhed with an exceeding great plague.</p>
            <p>It is a grieuous thing that a man profeſsing himſelfe to forſake the deuill, the worlde and the fleſh, ſhould break this vow &amp; couenant, which hee hath made with the holy God, the ſearcher of his heart &amp; vaines, and the iudge of the quick &amp; dead. But it is more grieuous when not only we haue contemned the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God, and proudly reſiſted his lawe, and defiled the image of God; but alſo haue giuen our ſelues to be followers of the deuil, and do ſerue him as a prince, &amp; a God in all vnholines and vnrighteouſnes for euer. But it is a moſt grieuous ſin, that in the time of the Goſpel we are obdurat in ſinne. For this being the day of ſaluation &amp; the time accepted, we turn it into the day of deſtruction and time of vengeance.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:15611:58"/> To ſtumble in the night it is dangerous, but to fall backward in the light of the Goſpell is damnable. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſinned but in his youth, we in our youth are wantons, in our middle age proud, in our old age couetous: and the older we are, the more wicked we are. It is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a man to ſin, it is the nature of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man to repent, but it is the nature of the deuill neuer to repent,<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> it a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the contrition of the heart.</p>
            <p>For as much then as the ſinfull generation of this realme of England will neuer repent, but ſtop their eares when God calleth them, fleeth from the Lord when he ſeeketh them, and ſhutteth vp their hearts when he knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to come into them; there muſt be either a generall tepentance, as there was in Niniuie, or elſe there will he a generall deſtruction as ther was in Sodom, which was in this maner. In Gen. 19.24.25.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.24.25.</note> 
               <hi>Then the Lord rained vpon Sodom &amp; vpon Gomorrha brimſton and fire from the Lord out of heauen, and ouerthrewe thoſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and all the plaine, and all the inhabitantes of the cities, and that that grew vpon the earth.</hi> Of this dreadfull deſolation you ſhall reade in Deutronomium 26.23. Eſay 13.14. Iere. 50.40. Eze. 18.49. Hoſ. 11.8. Amos 4.11. Luke 17.29. and Iude 7.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:15611:59"/>
            <p>Firſt, he is noted who deſtroyed Sodome, <hi>the Lord:</hi> ſecondly how <hi>he did raine vpon Sodom and Gomorrha brimſtone and fire:</hi> thirdly, from whence, <hi>from the Lord from heauen.</hi> The Lord which made Sodome &amp; Gomorrha a pleaſant and frutfull vale, for the ſinnes of the people brought it vnto vtter deſolation <hi>He did raine:</hi> the end of raine is the fertilitie of the earth: the Sodomites turned the fertilitye of the earth into <hi>pride,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> 
               <hi>fulneſſe of bread, idleneſſe, and vnmercifulnes to the poore:</hi> and therefore when this wickedneſſe was to be puniſhed, it was reuenged not with famin, peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or ſword, but as the wicked had peruerted themſelues, ſo the Lord peruerted the raine, not to the nouriſhment of the earth, but to the ſterilitie of it; and gaue them for dew, brimſtone, and for water, fire. <hi>Strabo</hi> in his booke ſeemeth to giue ſome naturall cauſes of this deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But <hi>Moſes</hi> ſheweth it came from the Lord, who is able and willing to puniſhe ſtrange ſinnes with ſtrange plagues.</p>
            <p>Further we are here to learne in that it did raine, that abundance of fire fell from heauen: ſo great is the treaſure in heauen of thoſe thinges whereby vengeance is to be taken on the reprobate on the earth <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.34.35.<note place="margin">Deut. 32.34.35.</note> 
               <hi>Js not this laid in ſtore with me, and ſealed vp among
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:15611:59"/> my treaſures, vengeance and recompence are mine,</hi> Moreouer where he ſaith, he ouerthrewe the cities and all the plaine, and all the greene things of the earth; we are to remember there are two ſorts of deſtructions: the one,<note place="margin">2. Sortes of deſtruction.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cities are ſo ouerthrowne, that after peace made they may bee reedified againe. Theſe kindes of ſubuerſions haue but a temporall ſcourge to chaſtiſe the wicked. The other, whereby in a perpetuall deſtruction both the inhabitants, and cities, and fieldes are vnreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerably deſtroyed So was Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha deſtroyed with all their inhabitants, and in all the plaine, with trees, herbes and plants: &amp; the monuments of this deſtruction remaine to be ſeene at this day, the ſhadowes of cities, the rockes exuſt, the earth full of aſhes, heapes of ſalt, a filthie ſmell, a dreadfull ſight, and a filthie lake.</p>
            <p>Here let euery good man thinke,<note place="margin">A note for England.</note> that if the Sodomites prouoked ſo great wrath againſt them which were guided but only by the law of nature, how much more deteſtablye doe they offend, which haue receiued the light of the Goſpel, &amp; yet commit the ſins of Sodome? <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.14.15.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>And whoſoeuer ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you nor beare your words, when you departe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:15611:60"/> out of that houſe or that citie, ſhake off the duſt of your feete. Truely I ſay vnto you, it ſhall be eaſier for them of the land of Sodome and Gomorrha in the day of iudgement, then for that citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 God doth not only ſay that the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Goſpell ſhall be grieuouſly puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but he ſaith, it ſhall be more eaſie for the Sodomites, and more grieuous to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of his word.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Right inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to be learned out of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorrha.</note> In this ſubuerſion are theſe thinges to be committed to memorie. Firſt, it is an eaſie thing with God to puniſh the wicked, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as eaſie as to ſend downe raine from aboue.</p>
            <p>Secondly, many waies hath God to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the wicked: the olde worlde he drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with water, the AEgiptians had diuers plagues, their waters were turned into bloud, the frogs crept into the kings chamber, they were puniſhed with gnats, flies, peſtilence, biles, haile, locuſts, darkneſſe, and the ſudden death of the firſt borne of AEgipt. The mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers in the booke of Numbers, ſome were ſwallowed vp into the earth, ſome were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire from heauen, and the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were all deſtroyed in the wildernes with fierie ſerpents.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:15611:60"/>
            <p>The third thing memorable is this, that the iudgement of God commeth ſuddenly: for when they were eating &amp; drinking, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and planting, ſuddenly came fire from heauen and conſumed them.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.3.</note> So <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith it ſhall be in theſe later daies: <hi>For when they ſhall ſay peace and ſafetie, then ſhall come vpon them ſudden deſtruction, as trauell vpon a woman with child, and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the wicked ſhal not eſcape when the iudgement of God commeth on them. <hi>Therefore the flight ſhall periſh from the ſwift,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſtrong ſhall not ſtrengthen his force, neither ſhall the mightie ſaue his ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>And hee that flieth of them ſhall not flie away, and hee that eſcapeth of them ſhall not be deliuered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, ſinnes do ſhorten our liues, for the moſt part of the Sodomites were no doubt in their youth, when the fire fell on them.<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.23.</note> 
               <hi>And thou O God ſhalt bring them downe into the pitte of corruption, the bloudie and deceitfull men ſhall not liue halfe their dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, ſinnes being continued, do alwaies bring newe plagues. The olde worlde was drowned with water, but Sodome was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with fire: therfore it ought not to be incredible, that all the worlde ſhall be burned
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:15611:61"/> with fire. The heauen of heauens is the Lords, but the earth hee hath giuen to the ſonnes of men; ſo he gaue a fruitful plaine to the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, but when they abuſed it, hee rayned downe fire &amp; brimſtone as plentifull as raine. So becauſe in theſe laſt times wee abuſe the creatures in riot and exceſſe, God no doubt will according to his word co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume the whole world with fire.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, they that liue wickedly ſhal dye miſerable. The Sodomits liued in pride, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came to ſhame, they were vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the poore, therfore they had iudgement without mercie.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, God will reuenge all iniuries done, eſpecially thoſe that are committed againſt his miniſters.<note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> For hee ſaith, <hi>Hee that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye.</hi> And Pſal. 105.15.<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15.</note> 
               <hi>Touch not mine annointed, and do my Prophets no harme. Cham</hi> for mocking the miniſter of God, <hi>Noah</hi> was curſed in himſelfe, in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in earth, in heauen, of God and of men: ſo the viperous brood of <hi>Cham,</hi> which ſcorne the reuerend fathers of the Church, ſhal be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed for euer: The vnclean Sodomites were burned to aſhes, and condemned becauſe they vexed the righteous ſoule of <hi>Lot:</hi> ſo our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:15611:61"/> ſhal taſte of the like fearful iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and alſo the whole land, for ſoothing them in their Iſmaeleticall ſcorning, if ſpeedilye and heartily they do not repent, which God giue them and vs alſo grace to doe, that we being deliuered from the dreadfull wrath of God, which hangeth ouer our heads for our many manifeſt and exceeding great ſins, may from one generation to another liue to praiſe the Lord all the daies of our life.<note place="margin">Num. 6.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 25.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord bleſſe and keepe this Realme. The Lord make his face to ſhine vpon vs, and be mercifull vnto vs, the Lord lift vp his countenance vpon vs, and giue vs his peace,</hi> for his ſonnes ſake Chriſt Ieſu. To whom with the holy ſpirit be all honor and glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
